He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and
bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as
made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening and welcome to the new,
earlier time.
All of you Dragon Slayers, Giant Killers,
and Mort-safe Movens.
You are listening to the 131st episode
of Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father-Industinvendemic and I'm a Espensalvania.
And with me is my fellow Neanderthal and proto-human.
Father-Steven D'Young in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And we are both...
perched above the gateway to the underworld that is planet Earth. We will take your calls
beginning in the second half. This is live. And the great gatekeeper Mike post apocalyptic
Kurgand again will be listening to your dulcet tones. If you just give us a ring at 855-237-2346.
Before I go any further. Yeah, go ahead. We have the elephant in the room to the grass.
Oh, no, for the people listening live, which is some set of
of the usual, some subset of the usual people.
You're already aware this is a different time
than we normally begin.
There's been a change in our live air time
and we've always been very transparent.
Father Andrew and I, with you, the listener
over the course of this show.
So I feel that we need to explain this, right?
to the 12.
listening audience. Why did we make this change? And so, again, just to be transparent, Father
Andrew, as he's continued to get gradually more and more old and infirm, requires certain
accommodations. And so, this is the first of what may end up being several things in the
future. He still has a few good productive hours.
every day where he can he can do some work and he's cogent. We're going to sort of schedule the
airing of the show around that. And that way, you know, we can get the most out of him while we
still have him with us. So I don't know if you wanted to make any further comment on that father Andrew.
or I just appreciate your...
I have to admit, this might not be a thing that I should joke about, but I have to admit,
with you as the CCO, I kind of feel like it's like weekend at Bernie's over there at the
should save headquarters? Well, I'm not at headquarters. Oh, okay. Okay. There you go.
Yeah, it's right. Okay. It's right. Mike DeGan is a headquarters. Simon Nelson is a head.
quarters. Well, I think he's somewhere in the neighborhood of headquarters.
Right. Well, I'm applying that they're the two guys who are kind of propping you up.
That's right. That's right. Well, I mean, definitely following on all of that,
we're talking about death, more specifically about burial. So what does one do with a dead body?
It turns out that this has actually been a pretty important question throughout
human history and
even before and we're going to begin by defining just what we mean by human by dead.
No, I did.
Yes.
What is this mortal coil that we shuffle off?
So yeah, why don't we talk about early man as it were.
Yes.
So yeah, and so we're going to be talking about here at the beginning.
We're going to be talking about early homo sapiens. We're going to be talking about Neanderthals,
aka, homonyanderthalysis.
And so, we need to say a few words, because I know there's certain people in our audience who are already triggered.
That's true.
Right, who are already running off to hide somewhere, or just angrily typing.
Right, I don't know if they're in the chat.
There's some interesting
going on in the chat. They may not be quick enough to be in the chat. They may just leave comments later
in the YouTube comments who are going to assume that as soon as we mention any of that is,
why are you teaching evolution? So we're not. We're not talking about that at all.
What you have to understand, and this is not like us doing some weird Christian
and ledger to Maine, like you can ask an atheist anthropologist.
this, they will tell you that everything or every one I should say that is in the genus
Homo, whether it's Homo sapiens, Homo erectus, Homo neanderthalensis, denisovins, etc., are
all humans.
Yeah, it used to be I think that some people had the idea that some of these other groups
where earlier forms and then there's other ones that evolve out of them or come out of them or whatever until we get to the floor.
Pre DNA.
Yeah, exactly.
Before DNA was discovered, I mean, so each of these groups is kind of grouped based on skeletal structure?
Yeah, certain elements of skeletal structure, bone density, all kinds of related things.
We find these skeletons. They're put into one of these groups and yes, the assumption was sort of
the evolutionary assumption that these went in some kind of order.
Right.
And what evolved from the other, but we now know now that we have DNA and we've been able
to get samples with the DNA from some of these remains that Neanderthals and Homo sapiens
and Denisovans and even Homo erectus now all intermarried and interbred.
Yeah.
Okay, baby.
So.
So which kind of violates the idea that these are separate species in the way that species
is normally defined.
And one of the proofs they were around the gentleman.
The same time.
Yeah, one of the proofs ladies and gentlemen of the interbreeding of Neanderthals with
homo sapiens is your two hosts because we happened to both be descended from the species.
Yes, yes, yes, two of the ethnic groups on earth that
highest percentage of the underthal DNA in the world. Yes. Northern Europeans in general have the
highest. But yeah. Yeah. So yeah. So this has nothing to do with evolution. You could, you could
everything we're going to say does not depend on you believing or not believing evolution.
it is irrelevant to it. Where
just talking about some interesting things you find at different burial sites for these
evil people but groups.
As is our want, we're starting back in like the Neolithic era.
So we're just talking about the earliest human burials that we have.
And we're pointing out as both religious and non-religious people would, both people who
or an evolution of people who aren't would.
that we're talking about early humans that includes the Adirthals for purposes of this.
So yeah, so even though there are still names as if these different types of early humans
were different species, they are in fact not because of the and the inner breeding proves
that. So we're
We're going to start with Neanderthal Barriels since Father Andrew and I are both biased toward
our own ancestors.
And so there are three really famous sites of Neanderthal Barriels.
The reason they're famous is that these are sites from which we learn particular things.
things about Neanderthals and about specifically about their culture and even more specifically
about their burial practices for the dead.
And now all of these, and once again our usual proviso on this show, we are going to be using
in the early part of the show, the first half and the first part.
the second half, we're going to be using sort of the standard dating that you will find
in textbooks.
Yeah, but if you, if you need to believe that the earth is of a different age than this
dating, yes, go ahead.
Again, it doesn't matter for this episode, what you think of the age of the earth.
Yes, we are not asserting.
Yeah, that this is how old they are.
We're just giving the standard thing from textbooks.
Yeah, you can readjust that accordingly.
We don't know and kind of don't care.
And you're right.
And the reason for giving it though is we want to give an idea of, you know, older, much older,
less old, newer, right?
That's the purpose of listing dates at all.
Okay.
It's comparative.
So, but you can adjust them however you want.
How are you see fit?
All of these Neanderthal burials are according to this.
standard dating from somewhere around 50,000 BC. Somewhere in that ballpark.
And Doug McClure movie. 50,000 BC. I don't know.
Maybe there's a 10,000 BC that's hysterical. Maybe that was it. Maybe that was it.
I used to watch all these Doug McClure movies when I was younger. Did you see those?
Like, he was always in these dinosaur movies. You know, oh, yeah. No, this wasn't a dinosaur movie.
This was a big but the 10,000
was a big budget. Oh, okay. Okay. They had mammoths pulling stuff up pyramids. It was wild. It was
utterly fictional, but a while. Yeah. Yeah. And related to what we were just talking about, they
This is so sad, but they found this woman, this older actress.
Who they thought kind of looked like a Neanderthal and so they cast her as the main characters grandma? Wow
Because they were trying to have like his little tribal group being wow
Like reflect the DNA integration. Yeah, it's like that's awkward
Yeah, so anyway
So the first one of these to talk about
And this one's primarily famous because of how many burials are in it.
And this is what's called Shannadar Cave,
which is in Northernmost Iraq.
Or Iraq if you were alive in the 2000s.
Or even in the, you know, I was saying the 80s, that's how they pronounce this is Iraq.
I ran in Iraq.
Think they're up to...
13 or 14 skeletons?
So each skeleton is numbered.
So it's like Shenadar I, Shenadar II, Shenadar III,
and it's like Roman numerals.
But so there are, this is a cave
that was used for a lot of burials as the point.
So there are a number of individual grave sites
Then I've been discovered in the K.
and those were discovered with grave goods, we're going to talk about what grave goods means here in just a second.
So that site other than just the number of skeletons is not super remarkable.
The second one, are you going to do the French since?
You know, you know, you know, you don't think I want to hear you butcher it.
Superior French scholarship.
I'll just put out like a
pronounce it like KJ man on sdl right that's the it's
Lashabella Ossan okay let's
the bello San yeah little
Chappelleoson like that yeah
uh everything just rhymes with
Quason like you force it by
tone community yeah yeah um
it's not he pronounced it out there in the
swamp I just honored my clan um so uh
that
As you might guess from the name is in France.
Yes.
But so what's notable about this site, there's Neanderthal
Barriolz there.
And there is a skeleton that was found there, Neanderthal
skeleton.
And it was in a, what's notable about it is that it was in a pit
That was
deliberately like there's tool marks and stuff dug out of limestone
Yeah, so not just like you know digging in dirt, but they actually cut into this
rocky pit and floor
Right and not like you know
We found a hole and we dropped the body in it right or right he fell there like this is very clearly a very deliberate
burial
that they went to
some significant
effort right to
To hollow out the the space
The the person who's buried there and this is probably related to the amount of effort that they were willing to spend to bury him
Was extremely elderly
You say, well, how?
How do you know that? Well, there we have the scale on his gravestone. Yeah, no, it didn't
have years like. Yeah, sorry. This is prehistory, which means there is no writing. There's
no writing. There's no writings. There's no inscriptions. But you can look at the skeleton
and there are clear signs of like advanced rheumatoid arthritis and osteoporosis. Right.
This happened to your bones.
right at old age. And so Father Andrew could probably tell us about some of those.
Absolutely. Every time I wake up in the morning for no good reason.
So this figure, we see that in the skeleton. And so that likely is related to the amount of effort
that was taken away. This was likely at elder, right, within the family unit or tribal unit or
or a cland-
it was, you know, however that unit was organized, this likely would have been one of the oldest people.
And also found with grave goods. So now here we'll make the note about grave goods.
So this gets argued about. So the technical definition of the term grave goods,
We are talking about like burial rituals and stuff.
definition of grave goods is not just, oh, they're they put stuff in the grave. Yeah,
with the person, right? Not like, you know, often one sees at funerals these days, where when
the coffin is open, there's there's stuff in the coffin. Yeah, picture. These were like a football
helmet and cheerios. Yeah. So no, this is a, these are things put in the grave that are intended
or aimed at being used in the afterlife.
So that makes it grave goods.
And so again, because we have no inscriptions this early,
we're gonna talk about, in the second half,
we're gonna talk about some later stuff
once we have writing.
So like with ancient Egypt, ancient Greece,
other ancient cultures, right.
We have more of an idea of what they thought
the purpose of these things that are in...
the burial site were for, right?
Could it tell us?
Or show us in pictures?
We have to sort of guess, you know, interpret.
And that's the word.
You have to interpret the things that are found
in these sites.
Right.
And so in the case of this and the previous Neanderthal site,
the stuff that's there is like Flint tools
and two
reindeer and bison bones. So the debate is did the people who did this burial
because the Andertals are people too, remember? The people who did this burial,
were they putting these things there so he would have them in the afterlife? Or
were they bearing these things with him just because it was like his stuff? Yeah,
like
were his personal possessions that they were bearing him with. That's the debate because
journal articles have to be written in anthropology as well, and desertations have to be defended.
So people go back and forth on which it was, right? And it gets into nitty-gritty stuff of
how you interpret what the raid...
here in bison bones were four. Right? Like was this a crude flute? Is he playing music? Or
is he, you know, like they'd have a ritual, right? You know, you get the idea. I feel like
the earliest flute was some kind of bison bone or something like that. Yeah, it was very common
to make things out of that. And why zents? Why isn't? Yeah. That's every reason why that is. Why isn't?
And in Europe, like in Doggleland especially the Edwrethals
mainly hunted reindeer for food, and then they would repurpose the bones and the antlers.
So like they made their spear tips out of reindeer antlers because they figured out that
reindeer antlers sort of splinter when they hit and lodge inside an animal. So it's sort of like a
hollow point bullet.
And can actually do a lot of damage and then bring down a reindeer more easily.
So, uh, you, you, everybody, you learn something completely irrelevant today.
But, uh, my answer is, I'm from in Toggleland.
I was gonna say, you said reindeer, uh, antler tip spears.
There you go.
I was gonna say probably a lot of this show is completely irrelevant for most people.
No.
No, it's true!
I'm just saying go how relevant you humble. I just don't know the rate your antler thing so much is you know
I mean, I suppose if you make a time of sheet you go back to like ancient doggle and and then like
A mammoth stomps on it and so you're stranded there at least now you'll know how to make a spear
So there you go
um
The third site
the third
sort of well-known Neanderthal burial site is the Cabara Cave.
which is in Palestine.
So you may have noticed, we've been talking about these Neanderthal burial sites, France,
Northern Iraq, and Palestine.
So this is across a pretty big geographic span.
Yeah, especially we were talking about the Stone Age where everyone is traveling on foot.
Yeah.
So this
skeleton though in the cabara cave is headless.
I mean, there's no skull. Yeah, he doesn't seem to have been like
decapitated. Right.
The skull has been removed from the set. Yes. And so that also is the subject of all
kinds of articles. Yeah. Yeah. Because there is evidence in a lot of early
civilizations.
much later than this, of skulls being removed from graves and decorated and different things
being done with them.
That's one of the hypotheses is that something like that was already going on at that time.
Then you get the counter articles that are like, we have no evidence of things like that
going on at the time.
then the response to that is, well...
maybe this is evidence of that going in the time.
Right. You see how academia becomes an endless loop with no resolution.
Um, right. But so we know for sure this is a burial site because you might say like, well, okay,
if the heads of this, like, how do you know he didn't get his head bitten off by something or
or decapitated or, you know, through accident or on purpose.
Well, because he's
buried with his arms folded over his chest. So that's a thing, which would be really unlikely
for someone to get decapitated accidentally or on purpose in the stone age in a way that would
cause them to fall straight back into a hole and flat on their back with their arms folded across
their chest. Yeah, this suggests being posed in that position. Yeah, right. The other really
interesting thing.
and evidence that he was not to
capitated is that
this skeleton actually has an
intact hyoid bone.
What's the hyoid bone on
the whole Steve?
The hyoid bone is the bone
in your throat
that is part of the system
that allows you to talk.
Is it the case that they
analyze these knee-and-earth
whole hyoid bones
and make this conjecture?
what we found. This is the one. Yeah.
because a highway bone is very weak.
Like if someone gets dies by strangulation,
their highway bone is almost always smashed.
Yeah, and if you get to capitated,
that thing is coming up.
Yeah, so we know he wasn't the captain
because it would be gone, right?
But also because it's such a small thin bone,
a lot of times just time erosion, right?
Like it's usually not one of the bones that's preserved.
the bones usually find or like.
femurs and right like bigger ones.
So more massive ones. Yeah. But so yes, as you are as you are alluded to, they have analyzed
this highway bone and its shape and structure. And so even though the endothals were much shorter
than most modern humans on average and stockier and had higher bone density, they apparently
would have had very high pitched even shrill voices.
Just imagine Michael Jackson in his later years.
Yes, someone who looks like Wolverine and sounds like Michael Jackson.
And we're descended from that you and us.
Yeah, probably you're relating while running at you with a reindeer horn tipped spear.
Everybody's imagining that now.
Now in a high pitch streak with Doug McClure coming to say so captain caveman led you all
wrong on this one.
Not even close.
You got to be serious to get the Doug McClure reference.
I think probably the other kids out there have no idea who that is.
No.
No, they don't know who John Saxon was either.
I'm sorry.
Who was that guy for like the entire 70s and most of the 80s?
Yeah.
So turning from UNI's Neanderthal ancestors to early homo sapiens burials.
Our earliest homo sapiens burials, again, this is going to confound the way some people
were taught this if you're old back in school.
earliest homo sapiens burials.
are way older than our earliest de-Earthol barriels.
Wait, what are the Earthol barriels?
Yeah, I know.
Cannot be.
Yes.
And by a lot, and biology class in middle school in the 1980s.
And so the earliest, as we said, the de-Earthol barriels we have are all from roughly,
give or take a couple millennia standard dating from that.
50,000 years ago, the standard dating on the two homo sapiens burials were about to go
over. The first one is around 100,000 BC. The second one is around 84,000 BC. So in both
cases, these are much older than the Neanderthal burial sites, due with that what you will,
adjust dates accordingly. But these are considerably older.
And these once again are in two fairly spread out parts of the world. The first one is the
Kafka cave which is in Palestine.
Now if you're following
This means yes that according to the traditional dating
There is a burial site of early homo sapiens
in Palestine that is
50,000 years older. Yeah, twice as old.
Palestine is very small piece of real estate.
Yes, but twice as old as the Neanderthal perials site there.
According to the standard dating, do with that what you will.
But the Cuffs of Cave, there are 15 burials there of early homo sapiens.
And there are graved goods there, and these are much more widely recognized as being graved goods.
And this is the product of racism.
Wait what?
Scholars have assumed for two centuries that the
The endothals were primitive and dumb.
Yeah.
And so that's why, so there was a belief
that they had no concept of ritual
and therefore no concept of the afterlife.
So even when it had to be admitted
that there were deliberate burial sites,
people still are pushing back against, right?
Like we also have the cave
that has the Neanderthal handprints all over the walls.
Where the antithyls put their hands in pigments and then made handprints all over the walls,
different colors, different color pigments. There are people out there writing articles that
that is not art because the antithyls were not capable of art. Right. So my ancestors are being
oppressed by the academic establishment. That's what I'm trying to say to you. Whereas, you know,
Oh, homo-
You find you find some stuff. Oh, yeah, that's grave goods. They believe it in an afterlife that you know, yeah, see how it is
But you find grave goods and their grave goods
Take more the form of and the read one of the reasons in addition to you know racism that they they want to
See these were easily as grave goods is that
that the things that are found there are
primarily shells and small animal bones that are often to work. And so pretty much everybody
agrees that they were part of jewelry slash adornment of clothing, right? That kind of thing.
They're not like tools.
They're
decorative and
therefore
they're seeing more readily as having some kind of ritual purpose.
The other interesting thing about this at other early
homo sapiens burials is that early homo sapiens burials have
little little pots, little tubs of ochre, which is a pigment
Brand Oze pigment.
Yeah.
And so the, the, the ochre is red.
There's a tub of red ochre in the, in the, in the,
coughs of cave.
Again, lots of journal articles about why it's there and what it's for.
Which runs again from it was an offering to,
it was pigment they used on the body.
Right.
So if you think like a red pigment might make the...
person look more alive. That kind of thing. So there's theories about that. That it was
being again, the skull decoration thing. So there's all kinds of theories, but it's not
always red, but these pigments are found with these early burials all over the place in
different colors and part of what.
The going theory on what accounts are the different colors is of course you have different stuff available to you in different geographic locales for making pigment.
And it's I mean, ochre is earth pigment. It's basically a form of clay.
Yeah, but you have.
It's not read everywhere.
That's.
The.
So that's that's all to be done.
But there are 15 individuals.
And then, here's another place that I don't even think Father Andrew
has a better guess than me on how to pronounce it because it's in Kenya.
Yeah. So like we're kind of pronouncing it the way you'd pronounce it if it was
Arabic, right? Like Pangeyasiidi. But it might not be Sayidi, it might be Sayidi or
side-eared. I don't know.
But can you in this call in let us know yes if you are a cadd
you
uh it could help us out without a pronounced the day with the place.
Uh the the panga I suppose could be pangia even but I think I'm pretty sure it's a panga.
Um panga yeah and then saidi saidi saidi.
Um it's a very early burial site in Kenya this is the one that traditional day 84,000 years ago.
And what's interesting about this is
that it is a toddler. So this is someone's young child who passed away and the body was
buried with a pillow under its head. And wrapped in some...
And this is debated too, whether it was just a blanket or a shroud or it's wrapped in some kind of cloth.
We've really got wrapped, you know, we've got scraps and remnants, right?
But was wrapped in some kind of cloth.
And
this one is the one of the really interesting things to me, because
foundly human, right? Like you have these images in your head of like cavemen and hunter-gatherers
and all this kind of stuff, right? But someone losing a child and sort of lovingly bearing them
with a blanket and a pillow, right, like to sleep, it's just sort of profoundly human and kind of
beautiful. We are. Yeah.
touching even about this super super ancient burial. Yeah. So yeah, we need to, we need to remember that
human nature. Let's say Paul wanted to teach us his trans temporal. They were humans, many of
the same sense we are. So why did we talk?
about these sites. Well, there's some interesting things. Okay. Because there are certain things
that all of the Neanderthal burial sites have in common. Even though as we said,
there's spread out over a pretty huge geography from like France to North and Iraq to Palestine,
right to the Levant.
And even though we talked about examples of...
like Kenya and Palestine, there are things that all of our earliest homo sapiens burials
have in common.
Just interesting.
I mean, that's pretty, they're not texting each other.
Hey, how do you do that burial thing again?
Yeah.
The element common and what's interesting is that some of the things that all the de-endrathol
sites have in common are different than some of the things that all the homo sapiens
sites have in common.
Yeah.
So what are some examples?
So Neanderthal burials pretty much everybody is buried on their back, right, like laying
on their back.
In that one case with his arms crossed across his chest, right, but always like laying down
Whereas all of those early homo sapiens burials, they're in the fetal position on their
side.
whether they're adults or children.
The Neanderthal burials are inside caves in these sort of dug out prepared spots inside
the cave.
Whereas the earliest homo sapiens burials are in or just outside the entry ways to caves.
Hmm.
Not in the cave itself.
So as we said, this is spread out, right, in both cases.
But there are these commonalities, right? And those are, those are kind of specific things, right? Like...
It's hard to attribute that to random chance.
Yeah, this seems to be a shared culture.
across thousands and tens of thousands of miles.
Right.
Among on one hand Neanderthals and on the other hand, homo sapiens.
Yeah.
Right.
That there is this sort of broad culture within these groups, with these certain
genetic characteristics of humans.
Right.
Um,
and so this,
if you're a long time listener to the program and you've listened to like the
episodes we did.
continuity, and we were talking about stonage stuff and everything.
This is one of the pointers because of course bearing the debt is a ritual.
Right?
And we're talking about, in this case, part of what shows it's a ritual practice is that
it's done in all of these cases, while these people the same way.
Right?
Yeah.
by definition makes it a ritual practice.
that this shared ritual practice, even at this very early date,
is one of the pointers to what we've called
the past early monotheism.
The idea that the earliest humans,
this is part of the evidence for that.
If you're talking about what is the evidence to support this,
humans had one
God that they worshiped. So yeah, we could suggest that this indicates a kind of pre-pagan human world.
Yeah, if you want to situate it within the biblical story, pre-tower of Babel, maybe even depending
anti-deluvian, part of the flood.
Right.
You better go on what you think is going on with the flood.
Because if the earliest groups of humans were all from different what we would call religions,
or at least worshiping numerous different gods, we would expect to see a lot more variety when
it comes to burial practices. And yet, what we see is a lack of variety. Again, this is all just
kind of this is interpreting what we see because there's no scroll line.
they're saying, this is what we meant by that.
It has a piece of evidence.
We're not saying, hey, these common burial practices prove
the worship of one that right, right, a piece of evidence in that direction.
Right. It could be.
That's, that's what we're saying.
So yeah.
All right.
Well, that's prehistory.
And we're going to talk about history, meaning, you know, stuff with writing
after we're done with our first break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen, David and father Stephen, DeYoung will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on-
next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient near Eastern texts such as the Ball Cycle, who tray the pagan god Ball as a rebel,
A hero of a revolution, worshiped and glorified for his long string of v--
In the Ball Book, a biography of the devil, Father Stephen D. Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the ball story on its head, depicting him as a failed and
defeated rebel who, nonetheless, tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
where the young works through the old and new testament passages that refer to
various ball stories and he surveys ball worship through followers, beliefs, religious practices
and liturgical life.
In these pages, we will see that the figures of ball and the devil, the Prince of Demons,
are one and the same.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.inscientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.inscientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, thanks, boys of Steve.
So we're talking about burial practices here
on this 131st episode of Laura Spirits Podcast.
And happy new year, everybody.
By the way, it's 2026.
Now, apparently, about the ballgame.
There we go.
I hear that ad. I'm just like, I mean, it's not wrong. It's not wrong. It's just, it
makes all the puns in your chapter titles, not yeah.
Yeah. So are you ready for a dramatic revelation?
I am. I am. This will show you the bizarre. We had a bizarre
wheeled wind and dropped off. So yeah, give me the dramatic revelation.
All the wheels within wheels that go on in my in my favorite brain when I write a book.
Okay, here's the great secret that no one has figured out.
The bail book is the Jungian shadow self of a rhizogod.
That's why they're roughly the same length.
I can see that.
There's even a structural thing going on.
That's interesting.
that is the mirror universe, or is it okay?
It has a go T and a little sash.
Yeah.
You don't have to have read or I so got to understand.
No, no, no, you don't.
As long as we're revealing things, though, I have to say those are completely not not on topic at all.
I'm just excited about this. I was telling you about this earlier today, father, that, that, uh,
A lot of people know that there's a film coming out
and just three weeks or so, a little over three weeks,
called Moses the Black, which I have to admit,
when I first saw the posters for it,
I thought that it was a joke.
And I don't mean that I thought,
oh, that's a joke, why did I do that?
No, no, no, I thought, I really thought
that someone was trying to be funny.
But no, there's a film coming out called Moses the Black
in a few weeks.
And I'll be interested to hear everybody's
response.
to it because and here's where I get to play my I'm still hoping to be cool card even here in my
decrepit middle age. I have seen it. I have seen it. And it's actually I think it's rather good,
shockingly, surprisingly, I can't believe it good. But it's, did you like the songs as much as K-Pop
Demon Hunters? I did not go away humming the music the way that I did with K-Pop Demon Hunters.
So yeah, you have that.
I know how you feel about rap music.
I am not into rap music and rap music is indeed what the soundtrack of that film is about.
But I mean, it could be no other.
You know, that film, it's about gang violence.
Did you shake your walker at it when the rap music started?
I did.
Okay.
But no, I, yeah, I encourage people to go out and see it in a few weeks.
I've never seen a movie like this in my life.
I'm not seen anywhere in the news morning.
movies as you have, but I've never seen a movie like this in my life.
It's just, it is not what anyone thinks of as Christian entertainment, but it is a
profoundly Christian film.
So anyway, yeah, go check it out everybody.
Okay, well, we do have some callers calling in to accuses of being Darwinists.
That's right.
We have one.
It's funny.
one that according
that his phone apparently is from Palm Springs, California.
But Adam is from Texas. So Adam from Texas welcome Lord Spears podcast.
Hey, how's it going? Hey, fathers couldn't get to talk to you. I actually am from
India, California, but I live in Texas now. Well, wow, India.
Where is that? Yeah. Is that your hometown area, Father Steven? Or I very roughly.
Roughly. Roughly? Okay. Very roughly. Inland.
And when I heard Paul Spriggs, I assumed you had grown up under the mayordom of sunny
bono, but I guess not not quite that old.
No.
I did just watch Groundhog Day and sunny bono figures over and over again in that film.
Southern Southern California has an Indio and a Chino.
Huh?
Yeah.
My dad was in Chino.
So what's on your mind, Adam?
Yes.
So on the subject of death and stuff, I was curious.
So there's Adam and even their kids.
They died, right?
Then you have after the flood, those people died, and then you have Jesus comes over post-resurrection.
And then it says in Matthew that holy people left their tombs and entered the city.
So what I'm wondering is.
It was that everybody who died before the flood and if that's true, then how is it that
like Moses is still around like in the transfiguration like like what?
Is there different things that happen to different people at different stages of history
when they die because I remember just kind of confusing to me.
Even in terms of like they go to different places?
The disposition of their soul?
Yes, exactly.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean so in terms of
of linear history, right? If we're thinking about history as human beings experience it.
That's where I'm stuck, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Before the harrowing of Hades, that Christ
accomplishes in his death and resurrection, all humanity goes to Hades. Now there's strong
suggestions that some parts of Hades are kind of better than others is the way that it's
sort of depicted the right just during kind of an
a nicer part, but then in the herring of Hades, Christ brings the righteous up out of the underworld,
and they're led by, you know, traditionally by the Archangel Michael to paradise. And then after
that then only the wicked their souls go to Hades and the righteous, when they die their lives are
hidden Christ. So, yes, so there is a difference before and after the
the herring of Hades.
So all of the, but like if you're thinking about the
transfiguration, what are we looking at there?
Well, because it was died, right?
And I know there's something about Moses' body.
It's mentioned something really special happened to him
and Jude, but it seems like Moses came, like was resurrected
from the dead before everybody else.
And also, you know, Jesus says Abraham Isaac and Jacob are alive
very least kind of...
It sounds like you say in that.
So I was wondering, how is it that they're alive,
but everyone else had to wait until Jesus resurrection.
And then now there's people still waiting for the resurrection.
Yeah, I mean, it's wibbly, wobbly, timey,
whimy stuff on a certain level.
Like the resurrection of Abraham Isaac and Jacob
is effective even before the herring of Hades.
not because they weren't herald in the herring of Hades.
It's that they're harrowing from Hades becomes
trans-temporal in its effects.
Does that make sense?
Oh, man, I don't know what trans-temporal means.
I mean, it's a cross time.
So like, the way I describe it to people,
even now is that from the point of view of the saints,
the resurrection has happened.
But from our point of view, it hasn't happened yet.
but we see that.
them as though they are resurrected because they are, even though it hasn't happened yet
for us.
Right. So, people who are right with God, when they die or have died, they're already
in a heavenly form, and then people who aren't right with God, they're just like dead. And
and they'll be resurrected when Jesus comes back to face.
is that however? Yeah, there's going to be so there's two
resurrections there's a resurrection of the soul and the resurrection of the body.
And the righteous are experiencing the resurrection of the soul immediately upon
material death, physical death. The resurrection of the body is in the future.
And the wicked do not experience the resurrection of the soul. They have
dead souls, but we will all have the resurrection of the body in the future. And
And the saved will be resurrected in both soul and body.
that that's that will be their final state, but the damned only in the body.
Gotcha. Okay. And then after the damned are resurrected with the body, they go to hell or whatever.
I'm getting confused with the hell terminology too. Yeah.
Yeah.
The Hannah are one of those. Well, okay. Um, so hell, Hades, you all the grave, I mean, all these things
just sort of names for the underworld.
In the end...
And what happens is the underworld itself gets cast into what the scripture calls the
lake of fire.
Yeah.
And so, yeah, the problem is, is that in English, we use the word hell to refer to a lot
of different things and then we kind of squish them all together.
Mostly like it's right.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, it is also the airport code for the capital of Finland.
So I just wanted to put that out there.
Like, there are literally there's signs everywhere in the airport.
They say welcome to hell which
which is awesome.
All that helps you.
Oh great.
Yes.
So great.
So amazing.
I met the devil.
Okay.
There's a reference.
Nexter's got you.
Here we go.
So I don't know.
Hopefully that clears up some of the mud for you, Adam.
It did a bit and I'll relisten again later to try to like reclareify it.
But if you don't mind really quick, the whole thing with time and how time works, I had
a question.
So
Daniel Archangel Michael appears and he says, sorry, I'm late because of the
Prince of Persia. You know, I'm talking about, well, yeah, yeah. How does that? How could he be late if they don't have linear time?
That's something I wanted to explain that one, Father Steven. Angels are still creatures. So they're still finite.
So they don't experience time the way exactly the same way you and I do, but they still are finite. So they
still experience.
time and space. Okay, and so they're created whereas God is not created, right? So God is like above all
that. But any, the same as like the same like say like the like the Théautocos would that be the
same experience of time? Would they both actually I think no. Okay. I think so, but that's because
That's because basically of theosis. That's because Christ didn't become incarnate as an angel.
Right. Right. So angels remain angels. Right. Whereas humans are united to God himself.
Next time I'll say that, that does make sense. Yeah. And that's made them a little lower than the angels,
but then kind of exalted above the angels in Christ, right?
Exactly. I remember that. Okay. Cool. Well, thanks very much for your answer. My question
for you. Appreciate it. Yeah. Thanks for calling Adam. All right. We're going to take another
caller. We've got Daniel calling from Florida. So Daniel, it looks like your question is similar
to Adams. Is that so? Do you feel like your question was just now answered? It's similar.
Definitely similar through lines.
So I'm
My question is basically about last week's episode
and how it ties into this one with price being incarnate
and the ascension and so in how the dead experience it.
However, my roommate and soon to be Godfather
of my first kid, Eric is incredibly shy
and he had a question about the infant Jesus
since it was close to Christmas time
and I told him how would I have
because our catacid couldn't figure this question out.
Okay.
So, basically, all right, my god, so if a person varies their father, they're unclean, not sinful,
having done anything wrong doesn't good, but just unclean. If you drop a big douche, you know,
you're unclean until you get washed up, but when Christ touched the dead, he essentially ripped
their soul out of hating and brought them back to life.
when Jesus was everyone's favorite six pounds,
eight ounce baby Jesus.
And he dropped duties
and the swaddling clothes and Mary had the wash them up
like with the unclean, with the ritually unclean.
Like, and I, we couldn't figure this one out.
So I figured I should call him
since it's in the church.
So the question is, is could,
could Christ have been ritually unclean?
Correct.
Especially when he was like a little baby.
Related to bodily functions.
duties. Well, it happened. Yeah.
non-synchal bodily functions.
Correct.
Yes.
So, here is an interesting thing.
I don't spend time arguing about this, but there are people who do.
I know.
Right, are you about this?
And I think the reason they spend time arguing about this is again, because they don't
understand.
It's not just that they don't understand the clean-unclean distinction.
it's that they don't understand that the sacred profane distinction has to do with common.
Right. They assume everything is like holy or evil. There's not this category of the
common in the created world. I mean, even the word profane, even though
this is not the way we use it in English, at least in its origins, it means something
that is outside of the temple.
It's what's not
appropriate in the temple, it's it's pro-phantom outside the temple. Yes. And we sort of use it like you think about profanity.
What's another word for profanity?
Volgarity? What does that mean?
Common.
It's the common.
Yeah.
And so
Right, the question really is, you're asking did our Lord ever...
get dirty. Yeah. And did he sort of walk through the world
pristinely clean, right? And. Because I was told women don't
poo per part. So maybe Jesus is the same. That is a lie. Wow,
we've gone. And I thought you said you were having a child,
which applies to me, you should be married. So you should know
Yeah.
Yeah, is she listening is that why you said no she's not so like
Oh, wow, okay, but it could give you out you know tens of thousands of people hundreds of thousands of people listen to this show
yes
so
Right and but they're related questions like the Christ ever gets sick
You're gonna cold
Drugs earthly life.
like pre-Dath and resurrection, right?
And so I think, here's how I approach this question.
And to pray for a St. Paul, I have no word from the Lord on this.
There is no dogma at stake here. But the way I approach this question is, by way of
St. Maxima's the co-passor, which gives me a little bit of confidence, not that he ruled on this
particular issue. But that...
when he talks about Christ having assumed the blameless passions, right?
Being the passions that aren't sinful.
Right.
So getting tired, getting hungry, getting thirsty, right?
So to me, I will not die on this hill.
But to me, the way I would approach that question is to say that...
At points in time, being blamelessly, right?
No issue of sin, right?
But blamelessly, ritually unclean, the way normal humans are in normal human life, right?
So it's in the blameless category, allowing himself voluntarily to contract that and then
Go through the processes.
prescribed by the Torah. To me makes sense. Right? It makes sense of the context of
blaneless passions. It makes sense in terms of you either may have recently or be
just about to celebrate the Feast of Christ's circumcision. Read what it
talks about in terms of him coming under the Torah. Right? It fits with that. Right?
because again, these
aren't right and I'm also not talking about
unclean ritual and cleanness in terms of
ontology right I'm not saying Christ was
tainted by the sin that is in the world
right but he certainly experienced the
effects of sin in the world like
receiving verbal abuse and all of it
right like that.
him voluntarily, right? You see what I'm saying? Right. So it's not that Christ became
ontologically unclean ever, right? But it's in terms of the ritual structure. There were
times when he would have been considered under the Torah, ritually unclean, and that Christ
voluntarily went through the processes to do that as any other person living at that
time would have.
I'm sure he'll listen to this
later and thank me for these
shy.
But I'll be brief with the
questions I actually wanted
to ask.
Got it.
All right.
Is that clear things up for your
unseen unheard from roommate
Eric?
Yeah.
Well, he's in the car behind
me.
We're caravading.
Got to move.
I'm sure he'll listen to this
later and thank me for these
shy.
as uh...
Oh, here we go.
That was my real question.
That was, that was really,
I was asking for a friend.
Yeah.
Uh, so on the last episode, you guys talked about how Christ took our humanity from Mary
that his humanity got elevated at the resurrection.
He's outside of time.
His humanity is outside of time.
It's eternal.
That's how he created man in his image and likeness.
for those of us, sorry, for those who have died.
have they already experienced like as a life of the age to come already happened for them?
Like I know we should still pray for our loved ones as though they're in a linear time, right?
Like that's what the church teaches pray for your loved ones. We don't know it the ultimate outman.
Well, we pray for them because we're in a linear time. Yeah.
Right. Well, that's the only thing we can experience. But I guess are they outside of that? But we should still,
I guess for the sake of trying to understand it.
We should still keep doing what we're doing, but I don't know what's going on as far as are they already experiencing that in the same way Christ's humanity is outside of time.
Right. So this is going to sound mean, but I'm not I'm not trying to be mean.
Okay. I don't have to say I'm done. I understand. I get.
I just know this is not easy. This is not easy stuff to part of Dutch and blood. But so your question is in coherent.
Here's why.
You're asking me what someone outside of time is experiencing now.
Oh, that's a good point.
See the problem.
Yeah.
What is now now is for us.
Yes.
We have now.
Yeah.
I mean, the experience we're having is the one we're having.
And so we function within that.
Right.
But they're not in another parallel timeline.
experience.
something now, right? Our definition of now doesn't apply to them. Yeah.
Does that help? I think so. I've been going to continue to listen. Like I said, I know
what I should be doing. I'm just trying to connect the through lines with eternity,
trans-temperolness, and these last couple episodes. Thanks, Padre.
Yep, alright, thanks for calling.
All right, well fun, good questions from last time and connecting this time as well because all this stuff
Is kind of one big ball of wax as we continue to maintain on this show that salvation was possible
For those early neanderthals and homo sapiens
Yeah, and the salvation that was possible was salvation in Christ
Yeah, because they should say humanity one salvation one humanity one Christ
Yeah. So yeah, so let's shift from through away from prehistory to toward history.
We're just doing toward right now, actually toward history. Yeah, yeah.
Well, let's talk about one of our favorite sites.
I don't know how many times this place has come up on this show, but less than go back,
Lee Tappy, I think, but maybe we'll catch up a little because we're not going to talk much about go back, Lee Tappy tonight.
tonight. But uh, channel Hoyak.
Good old Teto Hoyak intern.
I'm probably pronouncing wrong too because I don't speak Turkish.
But Turks call in, let us know how to pronounce this.
But only if you're Christian.
Exist is actually a question I refused to accept correction from Turkish Muslims.
Just unprinciple, solidarity for Constantinople.
So again, adjust your dates accordingly.
So we're not quite at...
written history yet with Chitalia. We are at conventional dating. Don't at me.
Nine thousand years ago. Okay, so this is one of our very early human settlements.
Right? Very old. Okay, but much more recent than what we were talking about at the
first half.
Okay, because this is people are now settling in places. We've domesticated grains to allow people to feed themselves, right?
So there have been neolithic revolution has happened, right? Stuff's gone on.
And so, this early settlement, we have a lot of buildings there, like actual, like constructed permanent buildings.
And what we find is that the barules
are primarily in the homes. So people were buried in the floors of homes. Either under the
hearth, just under the floor in general, under a platform, that seems to have been the normal
case for burials. There is one particular building in the settlement that is
referred to
is the house of the dead. Not because it is an old shooter game and a horrible U-bowl movie,
but it is called the house of the dead because in this one building there are 20 burials,
which is abnormal. So the general working theory, of course, you know, articles, right,
This retails
But the sort of working theory is that the people buried in the floors of what looked like homes were members of the family or social unit that lived in those homes.
Whereas the 20 who are buried in this one building are people who were unattached to those social units.
Right.
Um.
But again, we're pre-written, we're pre-writing so we don't have any, you know, we're theorizing.
The burials are in the fetal position, so we're going home to sapien style that has prevailed.
And there's clear evidence that these sites were repeatedly disturbed, meaning a person
would be buried.
It would be dug up again and for example another person would be buried next to them
Right
But also that during some of those digging up at reburials skulls were taken and
plaster and then paint was put on them and then they were re-barried
We don't know exactly what they did because where we talk about like plastered and painted
That means we've got little
and shreds of plaster and paint.
God's calls. Right.
So we don't know if they were sort of
trying to recreate what the person looked like
or they were just doing decorations
or if they were making some kind of ritual
thing being done to the skull.
We don't know if this was done at a certain time
like after a year or two years or
just when the next person dot, right? We don't have access to any of that, right?
We just know in general that it happened.
We've got lots of grave goods, lots of jewelry on people who are buried.
About the most interesting thing, the reason I kept saying family or social unit or
whatever is that again, we have DNA now.
And so...
When the DNA is tested on the people who are like buried in the homes, we've got multiple
burials in one home.
In most cases, they're not blood relatives.
Yeah, that's curious.
Right.
So, from our point of view, like from what we think of was normal, you know, life together
in a home.
Right.
So, yeah, we generally assume that like, oh, well, this is like a family home and they're
They're burying.
the dad generationally under the floor of the family home, right? That had been our assumption.
But that done work. So it may be that we have like married couples.
We don't know then what happened to the kids because they would be blood related to one of the parents, right?
So it could be that these houses were reused by different families that
Maybe a lot of these houses weren't used by settled members of the communities.
Maybe there was some kind of transitory population that would come and stay there and then move on.
There's theories that people from particular trades would form social units.
Yeah.
And so that's why they're not blood relatives dorms of some sort.
So there's all kinds of theories.
But we don't know for sure.
Channel.
Yeah.
Yep.
Well, I should tell everybody that when Father Stephen was putting together this research for
this episode, there was a glaring glaring omission.
And I'm really ashamed to be working with you based on this father.
But I mean, might as well just keep going, I guess.
But yes, so something else that is also really notable is there's a kind of burial called
The Kergen C, C, no not C, K-U-R-G-A-N.
And see I told you guys we only got a couple hours a day. I know I know that he forgets letters. I'm getting
It's already sundown over here
So a curgan is a burial mound. No way. Wait. You're saying there's more than one
Yeah, there's lots of them because
Khruggen told me there could be only one the only one. Yeah. Thank you
See that one I get
Yeah, so the earliest known Kurgens
seem to date from about 4,000 BC, but they're being built up until the Middle Ages, and
there's actually still quite widely.
And there's actually a few places in southern Siberia and Central Asia that are still doing
this.
So this continues even to this day.
They think that the origins of the Kyrgyn is the pontic or caspian step.
So Pandas is what is now basically Turkey.
So that region, you know, this is this is an Indo-European thing. So all of the Indo-European
peoples and that's a lot of us mostly think of Indo-European as a language but it's also
you know a historical genetic group too. Indo-European that's Europe that's people in the
Indus River Valley, India.
Now,
And so that area, it's basically all over Europe,
it's Central Asia, it's the Caucasus,
this is where you find Kurgans.
So it's hugely spread out, incredibly widely discovered
all over the world.
And there is this idea of what's called the Kurgan culture.
It's a hypothesis and the idea is that the Kurgan culture
was had its origins in the Caucasus,
kind of west of the Ural Mountains area,
and that the reason why you find Kergans
all of these various places throughout the world is that they all have the origins in
this one place. And it kind of semi sort of roughly maps to the spread of Indo-European
language as well, not perfectly, but kind of sort of. So it is okay. So it's a grave
mound usually for a single burial. Sometimes there are ones that have multiple people in
them, but it's usually just one. It seems to normally be kind of a high status person.
often they're dressed as a warrior.
If you think about this and make sense, there'll be a highest status person because it's
a lot of work to build a big mound over a single person who's died.
And in the ancient world, people die much more frequently than just mortality is much
higher in the ancient world, just premodern world generally.
So it's a lot of work, so probably not everybody gets one.
There's typically more men in these things than women, but there are some regions actually
where it's kind of 50-50.
There are various features in and around these things.
Often they'll have a moat dug around them.
There may be paths around them or two them.
There might be stone fences.
So it's not just a place to put the dead.
It occupies this place within the landscape.
It's a place where people are coming back to.
And one of the ways we know this is because there's typically internal chambers.
and often there are altars, whether inside
the structure or outside it and there be roofs.
So it's a mound, but then they've got,
like a hobbit hole, right?
You've got to build a roof and stuff inside,
so it just collapse on you.
So there's fire pits that could be related
to sacrificial activity inside and or outside.
And of course there's typically grave goods as well.
So yeah, you talk about pre-modern burial,
Cur-
are really prominent way that a lot of this is done.
And certainly there are other kinds of burial mounds.
I mean, in the new world, there are burial mounds.
And so the concept is very similar.
But archaeologists have noticed there's a distinct
continuity between all the curgans in Europe and Central Asia and so forth.
So yet another instantiation of this.
and it's it's um
It has a long, long stretch of history.
We're talking over 5,000, 6000 years that this is being practiced probably older than
the oldest ones that we've found.
But at least, yeah, 4,000 BC is the earliest known ones.
So yeah, Kirkans.
So two questions.
Oh boy, I'm not ready to answer questions.
Is this going to become a regular segment?
Father Andrews, Kirk in corner.
regular surgeon updates.
Yeah, yeah.
And secondly, are you expressing your final wishes to us?
I would not be against a curtain getting back to my Indo-European roots.
Yeah, no, I mean, I understand.
Are there any suitable mounds on Guam?
Oh, Guam Indian mounds.
You could, I mean, you could, you could put me inside Mount Lamb,
which barely qualifies as a mountain.
I don't know if that would be a good mound or not, but, um,
I don't know be very expensive ship my body to Guam
Unless you unless I go there to die. I guess that would be probably a little bit cheaper
Maybe yeah, yeah
Well, no, I mean those are much easier questions answer than I thought I mean I would be I'd be excited to have further discussions of
Kyrgyz here in l'Orospear's podcast
I mean this thing this first time has been mentioned, you know, so I
Know that I will in the future try to work it in whatever possible
All right, all right. I'm gonna have to do some more work on this clearly
That is a promise.
to you, the listener.
Yes. So, oh man, someone in the cat referred to it as a team
who period pyramid. How dare you, sir? Wow. How dare you?
That is on point. Wow. That is kind of on point.
Someone asked if you built too many curtains on Guam, will it tip
over? Yes. Thank you. That's the one thing we'll
you have no about no about glom as that it could capsize
Yeah, yeah, it is it is the lazy man's pyramid right let's find a hill close enough you know
But yes, so now back to the ancient Near East from our trannables into indoe Europe
Indoe Europe whatever
Eurasia, I guess be more correct
And we've always been at war with Eurasia is the thing.
So, specifically Sumeria.
So now we're at writing.
Now we've got writing.
And so as we go forward here in the second half,
we're gonna have sort of more and more information
that's solid, right?
That's not based on sort of guesswork
and figuring things out.
In Sumeria, an ancient Sumer, there's regular folks and then there's rich guys.
Ain't that just the way.
And I don't know whether they were engaged in class struggle or not.
That's a question for another time.
But the regular folks, we're talking about how regular folks were buried.
They were, like Chetelhoiak, primarily buried in the floors of their homes.
But this seems to be family homes.
This we've got cross generation, right?
If people were a little more well to do,
not like rich guy like the king, right?
Or major official or major priest or something.
But a little more well to do.
So this would have been like, say, Abraham's family
if he had stayed in Ura, right?
They would have multiple family dwellings,
within the city with kind of a courtyard around it.
And the burials took place in that courtyard
for the whole big family unit.
And people were generally wrapped in reed mats,
mats made of reeds, before being buried.
And often there are some sort of simple grave goods,
cause we're talking
regular folks. Now if you are a rich important guy like a king of priests, right?
It's important like the Ziggurat is not a tomb. Pyramids, tombs, Ziggurat's not tombs.
Ziggurads are temples. But so you're rich guys like your kings, your major
major court officials, your major priest of the city,
sort of the very wealthy people.
We're buried in large pits and large pit. I know it does not sound all that great
Well, you do believe in the land of mausoleums, so yeah, but
We're talking about the really well-to-do people in the base of the pit there would be these brick vaults
Vaults with walls made of brick right
So now we're showing off more of the well
And so there would be sort of a brick burial chamber for the person and then all of that person's slaves
would be poisoned when he died and
Not only were they buried down there with him, but they were posed
They were posed and set up like
doing whatever their duty was.
Wow, that's going on.
Stop.
Yeah. So, and there were of course in those tubes, elaborate graved goods. I remember the
definition of graved goods. We're talking about stuff that they believe was going with them.
So they had to have themselves in the afterlife, their slaves in the afterlife, and the accoutre
all. That the, that the, uh, slaves required.
so they could have the best afterlife possible.
Even though the Samaritan view of the afterlife
was kind of a horror movie,
if you're gonna be in a horror movie,
you want a lot of, I guess, slaves slash cannon fodder
around you to try and help out.
And remember, since it's very common
that these grave sites, whether regular folks
or quote, unquote important folks,
We're visited regularly and we're the sites of drink offerings
Libations as it were we're poured out
So this whole liquor thing into the ground is not just a part of the Irish problem, but is
Goes stretches back into ancient history. It's often wine honey
Let me...
That kind of stuff.
be poured into the graves, that sort of regular intervals. Egypt, of course, is kind of famous
for their burial practices. That's kind of their whole bit in terms of popular culture, at least,
and mummy movies. Let me just say it's an aside, right?
Uh, uh, Noah.
should read Anne Rice books. Okay. In general. No problem. But especially nobody should
read the mummy novel that she wrote. Why? No, I don't know. I had it is terrible. Really?
It is terrible. So true story here, right? So kids back in the long ago time, when you took
a long plane flight.
They didn't let you didn't have like a phone that you could watch movies and TV shows on and stuff. Yeah. Yeah.
You just had to either sit there or read something or sometimes there was a movie screen at the front of your cabin.
Well, everybody was watching your fancy pants flights. But
So there was a whole
There was a whole industry at airports of these bookstores that just sold like cheap paper graph novels
Paperback novels, right?
That people would just grab one to take on the plane with them
Yeah, right and we're not talking about like great works of literature here, right? We're talking about like, you know
a lot of pulpy stuff romance novels for women mystery novels, right, you know
Yeah, yeah, the best stuff you would get.
would be like the new John Grisham or Michael Crite and novel, like that peak, right, of literary
quality that they had there. And so I was the first time I flew to London, I was like, I need
to grab a book to read, right? And at the time I was 17 years old, was not in my goth phase,
that you know.
Where are they?
These head-right levels were supposed to be-
So cool.
I had never read an in rice book.
You had a goth face like everyone respectable had a goth face, my friend.
Oh, well, wow.
That was I too in a compliment.
I too once died my hair black and wrote bad poetry that didn't rhyme.
It's gonna hot top.
No, I didn't go to hot top.
Okay.
Once again, you do not understand the difference between like goth and emo and like vampire kids.
But anyone else I don't.
I mean, uh...
Our large German barbarians who saccharom that is what a goss is no no goth
This is like the goth category that would say burn down the hot topic, right?
Okay, but anyway, so
But I never had an ad rice book right
heard all these things all of our other books were series so they have this mummy book and I'm like well
This is a one-off
Right, I'll find out if I like and write novels how bad could it be?
It could be very bad.
Uh, base it like literally the dude is a mummy for like the first 12 pages.
And that's it.
It's over.
And no, then he's restored to his youth.
Wow.
So he just turns into this like ancient Egyptian Fabio guy and like it's a romance novel for
the rest of the thing.
Wow.
Why?
Yes.
with just cringey and lame sex scenes all over the place.
Like poorly written, like, and it's just like,
why, right?
Like, yeah.
So there you go, friends.
Do not approach that book.
Okay.
A loner in groups.
Yeah.
Where were some area?
In Rice Books, a general dough.
That one in particular.
Heck no.
Okay.
It's
back to Egypt. Back to Egypt. All right, yes, it's a modification. Yes. So but because this kind of
stuff is so well known and so easy to look up at research and learn about, we're not going to
spend a ton of time. In fact, I probably just doubled the amount of time we're going to spend on Egypt
with that mummy book story. But we're going to talk about
But, Barrow practices here in brief, sort of mainly at their
development. Okay, so when you go back to pre-dynastic Egypt, meaning before the old kingdom even,
you find burials that are a lot like what you find in the rexit of the ancient Near East in that
period, in that people are basically buried in oval-shaped pits. As you move through the pre-dynastic
period, burial start out being primarily in wicker baskets.
then move to wooden coffins and eventually move to sarcophagi.
The difference between today is sarcophagus and a coffin is that a sarcophagus is made of stone
and a coffin is often inserted inside of it, although sometimes just the body is inserted into it, but it is sort of a permanent fixture.
And even in the pre-dyedastic period there are extensive grave goods in Egypt.
Hmm.
And so a lot of people, there's a lot of evidence for this, that the earliest phase of Egyptian
paganism was primarily a death cult, not in the sense of going around taking people out,
but in the sense of being primarily concerned with funerary rights.
And the rest of their ritual practice developed out of that.
mummification as such began in 3600 BC, roughly.
And obviously they developed the process and the practice over time.
But all the way through the purpose of mummification is to preserve the body.
You
And essentially, the way it worked, again, they got better at it is you remove all the soft tissues,
like the organs and that kind of thing.
You wrap the body with spices so that in the super hot, super dry Egyptian climate, the
body sort of desiccates and the skin gets tanned like leather around the bones, essentially.
And then later on they developed Kenopik jars where the organs and stuff.
were contained and those are relatively more or less elaborate. Pyramids as tombs, because
pyramids were tombs. Let me also say there's a bunch of like bogus phony archaeologists out
there who are now, I found who say that pyramids aren't tombs and there's no evidence that
pyramids were tombs because they're trying to say they're like Atlantean technology
or something.
Um, I mean, there's literally after life stuff painted on the walls.
I mean, yes, like Stargates, there's literally sarcophagi inside the pyramids.
What are you talking about?
Yes.
Right.
Like, that's not.
Yeah.
Like, it's not even ambiguous.
They're, they're tubes.
Um, but uh, pyramid concern, the pyramids are much older than people think of them as being.
So pyramid building with the early step pyramids starts in the old kingdom.
And the last significant pyramid was built in the 16th century BC.
Yeah.
Like around 1550 BC.
So that's like the Bronze Age.
So they were done with the whole pyramid thing by the time you reach the Bronze Age.
And so yes, that means Hebrew slaves are not building any pyramids guys.
Yeah, they would have been pretty old probably by the time.
Yes, they built no pyramid pyramids were already ancient by the time that Joseph would have showed up.
So yeah, and so
the pyramids then were for Pharaohs surrounding them were mastaba tombs for sort of their
ranking officials.
There were as it, a sumer, human sacrifices at the burials.
It's not clear, it's not totally clear.
Whether like and summer, these...
were slaves owned by the people being buried, who were being killed and buried with them.
That was the general assumption for a long time.
But some people now argue that they were other people, like potentially people captured
in war and that kind of thing, who were killed at the burial to make them slaves in the afterlife,
to like the king who had conquered them, kind of idea.
And both may be true in different cases, right?
Or even in the same case.
So, yay, fun with human sacrifice.
Yeah, but so that was done.
And so when we talk about like the new kingdom,
the new kingdom burials are most of the ones that you've heard about and seen stuff from.
Because like the Valley of Kings,
we're King Tutankhamans too.
was discovered and other major Egyptian tombs that were discovered intact and
unrobbed. That's all from the New Kingdom.
And during the New Kingdom, those are essentially man-made caves. They're sort of
hollowed out of the rock in the valley.
And then during that period, commoners were basically getting coffin burials.
But pretty much everybody was getting involved.
Pretty much everybody was getting mummified to some extent.
Right.
Joseph was embalmed.
How much procedure went into that, right,
depended on who we're talking about.
But that was happening to pretty much everybody.
So panning out a little bit,
talking about the ancient Near East in general,
and what we're really getting at here is,
right we talk
about Mesopotamia, we talked about Egypt. So we're talking about the stuff in between the
Levant, Syria, up into Asia Minor, among Semitic peoples primarily, burials throughout this period.
So, the Bronze Age and into the early Iron Age. We're primarily done under the floors of Homes.
Still, right, for people living in cities under the floors of homes, they're primarily,
burials done where the person was wrapped in a readmat or in some cases placed in a jar.
A large clay jar. Both of those had the same purpose and held the remains together.
right in one place.
And people were buried with grave goods.
If we're talking about nomadic groups, right, so groups that weren't in cities and so
didn't have like a family home to bury somebody in the floor of, right?
Nomadic groups primarily used generational cave tombs.
So they would have a cave where multiple generations of that extended family or nomadic people
group would be buried. They would go to that place to...
bury their dead in that cave or cave system. We have an example of that in the Bible in Genesis,
and that's the cave at Makpala that Abraham buys to bury Sarah, and then Abraham is buried there,
the patriarchs are buried there. They're living nomatically in the region.
And so the patriarchs are buried there.
And what's interesting about these caves,
which would include Mark...
but also others by pneumatic groups is that discovered in these have been lamps, oil lamps,
right? So these are burials where it wasn't sort of sealed off permanently. The lamps supply that
people were again coming back again and again and again, right? That there was sort of a pilgrimage
site element of it.
The first hint we get of cremation in the ancient Near East is actually in a Syria in the
Assyrian Empire. While the majority of the Assyrian Empire was still doing burials, a few
of the ethnic groups, the small ethnic minority groups under Assyrian rule practice cremation.
That's the first kind of...
it's cremation we get. Next, turning to the last ancient
Near Eastern civilization, which is ancient Greeks, we have
again a lot more info about the burial process. So the
The basic pattern was...
an ancient Greece, that there would be what we would call a viewing.
So the body would be washed and then laid out in the home of the person who died.
And then people would come to visit to see the body.
And again, they would offer drink offerings.
offered a libations they would pour one out.
get not Irish. Um, and then so then there would be a funeral procession from the home with the
body to the place of burial, uh, with mourners like people singing dirges, limitations, right?
that kind of thing. There would also end the funeral procession in ancient combination.
Greek practice was also a sacrificial procession.
So if you go back to the episode where we talked about what Greek and Roman sacrifices
look like, we talked about how there was a procession to the place of sacrifice with the
animals that were being sacrificed, where there would be incense carried, right, and the
other things necessary for the sacrifice, because once they got to the burial site, sacrifices
were going to be offered.
And so those elements were also part of the funeral procession.
Once they got to the usually burial site, we also see in certain regions of the Greek world,
a minority of them, but in a few, there's evidence of this procession going to a pire for a cremation
than to a-
burial site. And it's not clear in the Greek case, some of those are in places where
they would usually bury. So there's lots of theories about that, right? Like whether
they buried at one point and then cremated and then went back to burying or some other
pattern like that, or if maybe the cremation
were tied to particular time periods. So think about like, oh, there's an outbreak of plague in the city. So we're going to burn all the bodies.
Yeah.
We don't know for sure. Right. But we know that there's this minority of cases in which, right, everything else was the same. But instead of going to a burial place, they go to a pyre.
Right.
And burn the body.
Um, uh, not.
Not only would these burials, and ancient Greece, be with grave goods, but food and drink
from the sacrificial feast that was happening at the burial site would be buried with the
person.
So this was sort of their last participation in the sacrificial ritual life of the community.
would then be.
after the burial, ongoing offerings that we know from written texts we're seen to,
we've talked about this before on the show, keep the person a lot,
keep their shade sort of quote unquote alive in its shadowy existence in Hades.
For pouring out blood at the base of the grave.
And that kind of well with these with with these with your regular person.
This was more drink offerings like wine.
Yeah.
Which was, you know...
talking about heroes. Yeah, yeah, it's a hero. Then they get blood. Right. Well, the founder of
a city, one of these major figures, then their burial site was attacked, literally attached to a
temple and the blood from the sacrificial offerings at the temple were poured into the grave. Yeah.
To keep their memory alive in the underworld. But you can see by those offerings that here we have
a pretty clear case by the time you're in ancient Greece that
the departed ancestors are being seen as semi-divine spirits.
There is an ongoing sacrificial interaction.
There are the recipients of sacrifice, right?
So this isn't, you're, you're, you're transitioning here in
instant grace, right?
In this respect that so previous grave goods and things,
this is stuff you're sort of sending with the person into the
after life so they'll be.
successful or better off in the afterlife in some sense. But there's much less of a sense
of an ongoing kind of relationship, right? Which particularly in the case of heroes,
you see here emerging in Greece, right? So you get something that could be called more
like ancestor worship. You also have somewhat famously in the case of ancient Greece, a
particular grave good.
right which is putting an oval coin and an oval under the tongue of the deceased
person to pay Karen the ferryman to get them across the river sticks without them
forgetting who they were and ceasing to exist. So you see this memory and
for getting idea. The other thing you see here...
because of that is the other transition you start to see an ancient grace, especially as
you get into more philosophical paganism is you start to see the beginning of a disconnect
between the person and their quote-unquote soul, right, their identity, them as it were, and the body.
That the
itself is not the important thing other than that site may be being a point at
which you can carry on this ongoing relationship. So then finally in our brief
pre-Christian tour of the ancient areas. We get to Rome and
As with most things, Roman culture, as it merges in the Republican period, has absorbed
a lot of ancient Greek culture but has its own peculiarities.
So they kept the coin under the tongue.
They still had the basic pattern of the body being displayed for mourners in the home, then
a procession, right? And then, uh...
disposal of the body, shall we say. But we get some changes. So for example, in the procession,
in Roman funeral processions, the the mourners who were part of the procession would wear masks
of the ancestors of the family to which the person being buried belonged.
So, they were sort of embodying the spirits of...
the departed ancestors who were now welcoming the deceased person into their
midst. And of course the big thing is that with the Romans,
cremation was the norm. Yeah.
What? Why? Like, do we know why there's this big shift that the Romans just
really embrace lighten them, lighten everybody out of fire?
I think they have...
They have fully metabolized the shift that was that we see going on over time in Greece.
So, if you remember, we're talking about the very early days of the Roman Republic.
We're talking about around 500 BC.
Yeah.
When we're talking about the early days of ancient Greece, we're talking about, you know,
for 500 years before that.
Right.
the archaic Greek period.
So I think Rome had more metabolized that.
So in Rome, there's sort of this disconnect now between the body and the person's spirit.
The departed ancestors could be sort of re-embodied by those in the procession.
Right.
Yeah.
kind of the full demonization of the dead.
with more of its original meaning.
Right.
Yeah, and so the body is just disposed of essentially.
And the ashes and whatever chart bone fragments remained were put into, earns often glass
earns in the case of a row.
Seat through, maybe?
which were then put into mausoleum.
niches. And also interestingly, but it makes sense when you think about it a little,
because we've been talking about all these other previous cultures burying people like in the home
or close to the home or in the cave, the door of the cave, right? Like you're keeping the departed
close. Rome, in Rome, the bear is always took place outside.
city or the interns of the earns were always outside the city. So this is and you know,
disposal. Yeah, there's a little more the disposal and also, yeah, right, you might you might be
thinking, right, you might be biased by the old testament, right, and you're thinking like, oh,
well, was it because the remains were unclean? No, it's actually the opposite. It's the opposite.
Once the ashes were in
they're the mausoleum, right? Because it was considered to have sort of the spirits of the ancestors
swirling about it, right? Was considered a sacred place. Remember sacred and profane is holy and
common. So the city is the place is the common place, right? The home even is a common place,
not a sacred space.
And so...
to be sacred, they put it outside the city.
So that you would have to go out there.
And that's where the processions had it.
The processions would head out of the city to the
fire and the place of, in term.
And then there is this massive wholesale shift.
Guess what it happens?
St. Constantine.
Wait, I was told that St. Constantine ruined everything.
I know
He had all of a sudden the Romans all start burying everyone.
Yeah, how about that?
It's almost like it's a Christian culture or something.
Yeah.
Who knew?
I mean, everyone should know since he is literally the best documented Roman Emperor in history.
But that's the one we choose to make up the conspiracy theories about.
That's right.
So you could go read all that stuff or anything.
Yeah, it's not like you can live.
read the text of every edict he ever gave.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, on that podcast of the episode,
for more of that rant.
On that true bombshell.
We're going to take our second break
and we'll be right back on this episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat five five.
A.F. Radio.
Poised between east and west, between Orthodox and Catholic,
Lithuania, the last of Europe's pagan nations,
did not forget its ancient tales such as that of the giant Tess Naringa,
Eglay Queen of Serpents, and the Iron Wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends,
with legends like
The heel of crosses and the miracle-working icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
In the Wolf and the Cross, Father Andrew Stephen Daymac and Deacon Sarifim Richard Rowland
take a very personal pilgrimage into a land where history and legend have met and fused,
where Orthodox Christians have lived as a minority for nearly seven centuries.
Their faith founded upon the blood of martyrs and the witness of dozens of saints.
to find this book.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF radio.
welcome back everybody. We're talking about burial on this episode of Laura
Spears podcast and we've just taken you on a short trip through pre-history and
history. And now we're going to get to talk about actual, actual Kristen burial
here at the very final half of this episode. We don't have any. Maybe wondering.
Why did we talk about all this Neanderthal and homo sapiens?
and all these things are cultures.
Well, we got to fill episodes people.
I mean, probably Andy doesn't want to show to end.
But also, there is a point.
But as usual, we'll get there at the very end of the episode.
Yeah. Yeah.
Make you wait until that.
Which I'm going to try and put off as long as possible.
I'm going to try to foil Father Andrew's whole plan
and just turn this into a four hour show now.
So it's a start.
You know, it's gonna be really hard for us to break the
used to hold the record multiple times over for
Interfaith Radio podcast length. And then Michael
Haldes did as a guest in the Umonsua podcast with
Father Anthony Cook. They did I swear it's like a five and a
half hour episode. That's not a challenge father, not
challenge except it, but it's crazy. I don't want to do
our 24 hour thing, man. We need to do this. Stop you.
where where is where if I have to do it alone I'll be like Fonzie in the dance
marathon I'll just be doing the caustic dance by the end of the 24 hours
wow I can have we can we can have a cycle of guest hosts both jump to shark like
you and I could start out and do like three hours and then we could just like
sub people in that's a great idea people in the chat sound off who do you think
should show up on a 20th. We do this for some kind of charity things.
kind of special thing.
I guess see if we can raise like, you know, tens of thousands of dollars in a day or
something like that.
Yes.
Do like 24 hours.
Wait till after I move.
Why you said you can sub out.
You can tag out.
I was going to say Simon and Micah sitting there going, please no.
They can tag out too.
I'll just wait till they fall asleep with the switch, you know, and then just say whatever
I want.
right yeah that'll be the real thing like 20 hours in when I start getting punchy
imagine what I'll say then yeah yeah
if you know someone says we need a Jerry Lewis style marathon there we go now like the old
telephone I used to watch I mean well my grandmother watched those and you were at her house sometimes
well what is going on yeah yeah oh yeah they'd have this celebrities answering the phones
Yeah, oh, so
Someone thinks that we should bring on pastor Mike Lansman to cohost this with you.
Oh yeah.
You'd be up for that?
No, each Lansman on.
Each of the person who subsids, they're also all going to get roasted like the second.
Well, I mean, that's a foregone conclusion.
They come on the air.
Yes.
Exactly.
Which could be awkward, depending like, you know, all of a sudden you throw Malinda at
me in the morning or something.
And I just don't.
Oh, she can hold her own buddy.
Bye bye.
Serious.
can't. Yes, she is. In fact, you know why she drinks no coffee? It is because she is naturally
accaffinated. Yeah. Oh, yeah. She is tough as nails. Yep. Yep. Yeah. So challenge accepted.
Oh, yeah. So true story. True story. The first time I met her husband, I just instinctively
roasted him. Oh he's a great guy too father Mark.
Yeah, he's the man. I think he took it very well. It was literally like the first thing I ever said to him
Yeah, he didn't know me at all, but yeah
Yeah, he's
Yeah, no, he's just a great great guy
Yeah, you want to hear that story by the way sure why not we got a little extra time obviously since you want to stretch this episode
Be five hours. We're at the we're at the Antiochia village
He and I butch other clergy
Uh...
as one does. And one of our one of our compiers was serving Eric,
which at the time he had not had before. No. And so I came and got some, he's just learning about
it right now. I came and got some and I always get mine straight up like I don't add water I don't
add ice right. And so we had never bet I walk out next to him. He just give it to me straight up.
I get he's like oh why don't you add what?
and I said, for the same reason, I don't wear a dress.
And that was how we met.
Wow.
All right.
Kristen burial.
He took it very little, like I said.
Oh, yeah. He's just a good dude.
Yeah, Aaron, he's got St. Anthony.
He's searched out there in Butler, Pennsylvania, western Pennsylvania area.
Don't dox the man come on. I mean, you know, you can look this up on the inner webs
I'm not telling you where it lives
Okay, yeah
See to it you don't sir. Yeah, it might cost you your job
Yes, no dox the boss's husband. That's always yes a good base. You're kind of doxing the boss when you do that well again
Presumably
Yeah, yeah, so any calls?
No, no, no
people are either satisfied or they just have no idea, you know,
whether it's just they're such confusion from having just tuned in and being like,
what's going to the show start?
Yes, right. All those people over like, like right now, you know, in Chicago,
it's 7 p.m. And so some people are just now finally getting home when they left
the office at five. Um, so, so that so to the listeners who are feeling that
That sense of disorientation you have right now is
what Father Andrew was dealing with. That's why we're starting early. So yes, here in
the third half, we come to Christian practice. And as usual, by Christian, we mean Orthodox
Christian. Yeah. Sorry, not sorry. That's everything we're going to talk about in this
section.
in terms of how these things are done,
goes back to the ancient church.
This isn't like, none of this is loopy stuff, right?
Like none of this is like something
we came up with last week.
Not that there's any of that, the Orthodox church,
but that's what justifies us saying.
So, in Christian practice,
one of the things that we inherited
from second-temple Jewish practice.
is holding vigil with the body of the deceased person.
Yeah.
And during that vigil, traditionally, the Psalms are read.
Yeah, unfortunately, a lot of funerals these days, you don't see that.
But I think especially with clergy funerals, there is a big effort
to have people come and read Psalms.
I know some community
are really, really serious about this.
So if you're in one of those parishes
where they're really doing like a vigil
over the body of people who die in your church
with Psalms and stuff, good for you.
I mean, this is how it should be done.
Yeah, yeah.
And I did it.
I did it for my dad and I actually did it
for a few people.
I don't know if they even know where their families know.
I did it for some of the folks in West Virginia.
It's a powerful thing when I was up there.
It is.
Not only is it something to do as a community, but if you're a family member, it's a very powerful thing to do.
Yeah.
Yeah. And I mean, I remember it's not quite the same thing, but it's very similar.
I remember when my, when my mother was, was dying and she was in her last days where she was in hospice for a while and then she came home.
You know, and I had already talked to her privately, kind of, you know, asked for forgiveness for every stupid...
thing I did when I was younger. And at one point, I didn't know there's not much more
to be said and honestly, also like her, because she died of brain cancer. And so it was affecting
her ability to talk. Thank God, brain cancer doesn't hurt, doesn't physically hurt, but
it does, you know, it limit her ability to express herself. But we still were able to communicate
well, but it got to the point where it was starting to get less and less. And even though she was
gone yet. Eventually, I just went and sat with her and I read, like, I read the gospel of
John in particular when I was with her. And I don't know, there's just something about it
that just really just worked, just really, really worked. And I know also like there's, there's,
like, I know at the beginning of the funeral service, right, the Psalm that is there is actually
like an exorcism Psalm.
And so I think, isn't it, is this, this, you know, reading the Psalms or the body in the
vigil before the actual funeral service proper, is something like that going on here as well.
There's a sense of like, okay, here at the, this transition between this world and the next
dark powers kind of attack, you know, or our present or whatever.
And there's certainly temptation, especially for those of us who are living.
And so there's a sense that reading the Psalms.
is spiritual warfare.
Is that what do you think? Is that I know that that's Psalm certainly that's at the
being in the funeral service? Yeah, no, yeah, that's it. That's the next racism's halt. Yeah.
Yeah. So yeah, yeah, there is that there's there's a whole bunch about because if you read the whole
sultar. You have sombs, several sombs like that. You have sombs that are expressing grief and
spare that people are feeling right at that time. Yeah.
Oh,
expressly to God in a holy way. Um,
I mean, the Psalms got everything. I mean, you know,
yes, it runs the gamut, right? And so yeah. And you know,
the Rubinic Judaism has held on to a form of this tradition from
second temple Judaism to and they call it sitting Shiva. Um,
with the body.
Yeah, but that that comes from the common
Second Temple tradition. So it is a good thing to do and places will let you do it
Right, even if it's not something that like your church regularly does or if it's happening in a funeral
Like if you ask they will let you do it
Yeah
I mean, and the ideal is that, that, you know, when the time comes at the
brought to the church and simply left there. And then you so you know what better place to stand
there and read the Psalms. Yeah, we're sit there and read the Psalms. Then in the church next to the
body. Yeah. And so that traditionally there are there's a traditional orthodox burial shroud.
Sometimes that's not used but there is one. Yeah, you can order one, right? You can get one. They're
they're not super expensive.
No, they're not actually there. I mean, like they're often just printed now. So like yeah. Yeah.
Um, traditionally the body is facing the altar.
Yep. Yep. Because the person is still part of the worshiping community
uh, and is open. And a big part of the purpose of it being open is that traditionally before
or the Coffinor casket is closed, the body is...
venerated. You know, one of the things that I've seen, which I thought was kind of cool,
and I was a little bit envious of because it's not in our tradition. I was at a Ukrainian funeral.
And they, the towards the end of the service, I was just thinking about this because the shroud,
um, towards the end of the service, the priest will take out this little sort of headband that
gets put on the body. And as I recall that he said something like
you're crown of glory. And I was like, Oh, man, that's cool. And I've not seen it in any
I don't know if it exists in other traditions, other Orthodox traditions. But yeah, and
it was printed like it was printed with, I don't know, I think there was crosses and maybe
I don't know. There was probably writing on it as well. I didn't get a close close look
at it. But yeah, I mean, the way that you dress the body is really important traditionally.
Yeah.
And yeah, the body is venerated because we are, of course, made in the image of God.
So every person is an icon of Christ.
And then, of course, we have the funeral service proper.
We're not going to go through the whole orthodox funeral service right now.
I mean, we could because we've got this extra hour.
Maybe we should do that at some point is actually go through all the parts of the funeral service.
I think that would be a really interesting episode all on its own.
like I could
do a whole episode just on say John of Damascus's canon.
Oh, the Federal Service.
Like, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Easily.
Yeah.
There is traditionally then a procession to the cemetery.
Now,
in a lot of modern practice,
that takes, it's up, taking out a different form
and then it gets kind of interrupted.
There's like a procession out of the church to the car.
Yeah
Yeah, then there's a car everybody drives the cemetery and then there's a
procession from the hers to the gravesite. Yeah, the best is when you've got,
you know, the cemetery is near the church and you can simply go right there.
That's nice. You can do it the traditional way, but that isn't happened a lot in
modern life in a lot of the countries where people are listening to this right now.
But if you have that advantage, great, right?
but there is singing
of him's at which him's different a little bit depending on your tradition, but there is singing during that procession.
And then the grave site is blessed.
The burial happens.
Yep.
And the person is buried...
facing east. I remember you know at our own
the modern of course St.
T. Con's has a grand Orthodox
cemetery and it's interesting that
across the street from St.
T. Con's cemetery is is it East
Canaan Bible Cemetery or something
like that. It's really striking how
at St. T. Con's cemetery all the graves
are boom facing east and then right
it across.
the street, there's a whole bunch of different orientations. Yeah. You know, it was that pun intended.
No, it wasn't actually. No, it was not. Okay.
Tell me, this is why I need to go to bed earlier, father Steven, as you know, my etymology is leaving
me. Yes, you should be oriented toward the orient. That's all right. Yes.
I'm
experiencing a lot of decay. The east of the highest. Yeah. So, part of the blessing of the
Graves is that it would remain secure until the time of the bodily resurrection. Yeah.
The, now there's exceptions to that. So, for example, Greek burial practice, people are exhumed and then
We are Bonson.
washed by the family with wine and put into wash worries that are then put into
mausoleums. Yeah, it's because the space for burials is just not nowhere near
much. And I wish I knew the name of the show but there was that there was an NPR
podcast a few years ago. That's really interesting because they did a story,
it's a woman telling her story and she was this sort of mostly secular Greek
woman who is technically orth...
the dogs, but did spend a lot of time in church. And, but she got invited back to Greece to
do that with her mother. With her mother's remains. And did it. And she sort of talks about
all the feelings and stuff involved. And like the horror as an American, at the idea of,
you know, touching it, mostly decomposed love one, right?
Yeah. But then how that experience changed her view of herself and her family and her culture
and her faith and all of that stuff. It's really good. Another story that I wish I remember the
details of is one that my wife was telling me just this morning after she heard us talking about
about this episode. I think I don't think it was around here, but
There's it's this sort of folktale.
It might have been up in Minnesota of this Roman Catholic guy who died in this
Lutheran area.
And he had insisted his last wish that he'd be buried in consecrated ground.
But the Lutherans just buried him in a cemetery.
And so apparently his vengeful ghost has come back to haunt the Lutherans.
Hey, like ever since that area.
Yeah. Take that. But anyway, yes. So then after the burial, there's a shared meal with
the community called the Mercy Meal or Makaria if you're in a Greek church, they called
the marketer. I don't have to do the macarena. Oh it goes. Wow.
Could do the macarena at the macaria. It would be very
out of place, but but
uh
So oh you know there was a period of time
where that was happening.
I hope not.
I would die instantly of cringe.
Um I just and it's something that's that's
we're an interesting variation is a clergy funeral.
Um so orthodox clergy funerals are a bit
different. Well, so part of this is, I will let you go, but yeah, part of this is that a lot of the
traditions that have fallen into a little bit of disuse in regular funerals are still done
every single time with clergy. Oh, sure. Yes. Yes. So part of this is this is a more antique form of the
Yeah, that's true, but some is still particular to the clergy no matter what yeah, yeah, yeah
Thank you for that. I'm gonna let you finish.
Yeah, so clergy are buried in their vestments.
And one of the things that's done,
and this is actually something that most people
will never will see.
But I have done this a few times.
So who vests the clergy?
Well, it's not the funeral director.
It's other clergy.
So now funeral director may be there to help.
because frankly, if you know a director knows how to deal with a dead body in a way that your average priest probably not as experienced with.
But yeah, so I've participated in a number of times in the vesting of a deceased clergyman.
And it is actually a really powerful, beautiful, amazing thing.
Often one of the clergy will be there reading the Psalms.
Another may be sensing.
the body, if there's enough clergy to do this with a sensor, and then the rest of us
will, you know, vest him. And as you vest him, you read, have you ever done this father?
Have you ever done this for another clergyman?
I have not. I have not. Well, of course, you're like out in the middle of, you know, far fewer.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'm in Pennsylvania. You know, we've got 250 orthodox churches.
So yeah, I've done it three or four times as I recall.
And as as
each item of the vestments are put on him,
then the prayer is said that is said when normally,
because as we put our vestments on,
each piece has a prayer that goes with it.
People, again, may not know that
because most people are not around with us
and they alter more putting our vestments on.
But he's being vested, the prayers are being said
on his behalf.
And there is a custom, it's not always followed
because sometimes it's not practical,
but there is a custom of getting buried
in the vestments that you are ordained in.
So kind of back to the beginning.
And actually, when I saw that my ordination investments
were getting a little bit worn, I folded them up
and put them away.
And I'll bring them out once a while, maybe once or twice
a year to wear them.
But the idea, basically, is that I'm saving them for the end.
Yeah, yeah.
And then there's some other interesting peculiarities, depending on what rank the clergyman is.
So obviously they're invested in their vestments. But if it's a deacon,
then he has a sensor put in his right hand. And traditionally, he's buried with him in the coffin.
And so, you know, practically speaking, what might be done is to take like an old sensor.
you know one that's ready to be retired anyway and you know and then
and send that off with him.
But he may well have gotten a sensor for his burial.
That's definitely a possibility.
Priests and bishops.
The Iyer, so the cloth that is placed over the chalice
and the discos, the big one during the divine liturgy,
traditionally that is placed on his face
throughout the whole funeral service.
Now in many cases they'll take it off.
People like, oh, I wanna see his face, whatever.
but traditionally...
it is placed on his face and covered. And it's not because they're trying to hide his face.
It's like, well, what other one thing is this cloth used for? It is to veil the bread and the wine
that are about to become the body and blood of Christ. And so it is it is valing the face of the clergyman
to show him honor, show him respect,
to connect him to the divine liturgy in
one final way, right? But then also priests and bishops will be given a gospel book to hold
in their coffin. And again, sometimes it's an old gospel book that's ready to be retired,
but many clergy will also buy one specifically for this purpose. And sometimes they're smaller,
you know, than the big, the full-size gospel that you'd see on an altar. But sometimes it's the same
So, again, it's to connect that.
And then there's a custom.
And I think you were saying it might be peculiarly anti-Okin.
I don't know.
Yeah, I don't know if anybody else has it.
Yeah, there is a custom that when the mother of a priest is buried, that one of his epithrochelia,
his priestly stole, the core investment that marks him out as...
priest that that is folded up and placed under her hands in the coffin with her as an indication
that this is the mother of a priest.
I've heard of it being done.
I don't think I've actually seen it.
This causes a brief fracas between myself and my mother.
Yeah.
Well, your mother is still living, of course.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, my mine is not I didn't do it I had heard of it, you know, I didn't do it with her
She she was not buried in a Orthodox Church so
Yeah, I didn't do it with her
But I thought about it, you know the thought definitely came to me when I was at her
No, my mother sent you wanted this and I of course being
Dutch and stingy was like well
I said I'll get one for you. She's like no I want one you've used and I said that would break up
one of my vestments sets, and those aren't cheap, you know, like being cheap. But this
was resolved because my very first set of vestments, what I was first ordained to priest has
gotten kind of old and worn and has been retired. Yeah. So the compromises will use the
stole from that set, say, because it's been used. But I don't have to worry about breaking
up the set. Yeah. One thing that's peculiar about
Um, bishops and priests is they actually kind of have two funeral services.
So, um, there's the V funeral service that is done for sort of everybody.
But then usually the night before, although sometimes I've heard of it being done the same day, same morning, whatever, there is a service called the funeral service of a priest, but it's not the end.
But I don't know why in the books it says the funeral of a priest or whatever.
But yes, it says other servants
that's done typically the night before. So yeah, varying a priest or bishop is a multi-day affair
typically. And I know that like particularly in the Slavic tradition that I think the canon of
Paska is sung. I don't we don't do that, but the canon of Paska is sung as part of the funeral
of a priest. And then one thing that's peculiar to bishops only. So everybody else when their body is
in the church.
during the funeral service, the feet are facing to the altar, so it's like they're in church, you know, attending church, right?
So that they're faced, if they sort of set up, they would be facing the altar. With the Bishop, it's the other way.
He faces the people. And that's because of
his place as the celebrant of the liturgy and the one that is bringing Christ to us, you know,
as the, you know, at Parax Alliance, so to speak.
So it's an interesting element in a Bishops funeral.
So yeah, it's, I don't know.
It might sound weird to say this, but I love our funerals.
They're very, very powerful experiences.
And I've known people that their first experience
with the Orthodox Church was an Orthodox funeral
and seeing that like whoa these people take
in the resurrection really seriously. I need to check this out. I need to see what's going on
here because I mean we haven't gone over the actual text in the funeral and got I think I think
we should do an episode about this but it's so explicit. It talks about death. I mean it talks
about worms you know eating the body and this kind of thing. So it really faces it head on. There's
no celebration of life you know kind of thing going on there. No no no it's about death. Well I'm
I'm gonna add that in between.
What I go, there's gonna be a...
extra service, right? Oh, a celebration of life? No, at the local
tavern, everybody's going to get drunk and tell funny stories about
me and eat ham and cheese on a roll. Well, wouldn't want it to be
too expensive after all. That's a Dutch funeral thing. Yeah.
I'm telling you, anybody out there who's been to a Dutch
funeral, right? Ham and cheese on a roll.
Ham and cheese on a roll. What I was what I was doing the Dutch
perform pastor thing, right?
I wasn't married and I was doing funerals and my fridge was just full of freezer bags full
of ham and cheese on a roll because I had all the leftovers. Wow. Yeah. But yeah, when I
kick off other interview, there you go. Okay. Do you know we got a couple of stories? Ham and
cheese? You really noted, I mean, despite your claims about my dissent into the underworld,
you're probably going to go before.
for me as we all.
You could mullinger for who knows how long.
That's true.
There is someone who asked a question in the chat, which I think is very, it's quite salient.
So someone asked, do you have to be embombed for all of this?
In other words, all of everything we just described to go on.
And she says it feels like it would take a while.
I don't want to be embombed.
I have a stranger version to it.
So the answer very briefly is no.
It is not required to be embombed.
The only reason why I'm bombing takes place is to be because there's days between...
death and the funeral these days. But even then, even then, frankly, there's refrigerators
that most, you know, undertakers have. So it's not really necessary. And in bombing, frankly,
is caused a bunch of money. It's one of the reasons that people think that that burial is so much
much more expensive than cremation. That's not actually always true.
Yeah, embomming is not required.
I mean, different states have different requirements about all this kind of stuff, but I think most
of them permit, you know, refrigeration, frankly, if there needs to be some time between death
and the actual funeral, you know.
But here's the thing, if you get embalmed, you can be very sure that you won't be buried
alive.
That is true because you will not survive being embossed.
That's pretty cool.
Lots of vibes.
the above the process. That's right. Yeah. Yeah. Um, yes, absolutely. So yeah,
good question there in the chat that comes from Brienne. So Brienne, great, great question.
That's that's a good one to ask. Oh, and by the way, update from my career. If you want
to know more about the Roman Catholic guy, haunting the Lutherans in middle way West Virginia,
That's where it is.
Mm-hmm.
Look up.
the legend of wizard clip. That's a great name. Yes. Oh, the legend of wizard clip.
That's great. You know, the other thing I'll say about all of these funeral practices is
there are now many Orthodox churches in the United States. I can't speak for other places, but
there are many in the United States that have a burial ministry. So people within the church
have learned all of this.
And they basically, in most respects, almost everything that could be done by a funeral home
can actually be handled by a ministry of the church.
And I have seen this done and why was it so much better?
Nothing against, you know, undertakers.
I'm friends with one here.
He's very, very good.
In fact, he's orthodox.
He's very good.
But, but parishes that take this over.
It's a really a beautiful, wonderful, excellent, powerful, powerful thing to do.
So I mean, there is a book called, I think it's called a Christian ending by Perturde
Can Mark Barna.
Is that right?
Is that the one that kind of describes all of this?
How to do it?
I think that's what it's called.
And yeah, people have used that as a kind of manual to learn how to do this ministry.
So I mean, if you're in your church and you're, and this.
You know, you find this moving, you find like that you feel a desire to do this kind of ministry.
Look this up. You know, have a conversation with your priest about it. See what could be done.
Obviously, local laws can sometimes govern what exactly is permitted to be done.
You know, without being an actual funeral home. Yes, you're going to need somebody to dig the grave.
You might need a backhoe for that. Whatever.
but yes there's so much that can be done and honestly also honestly
You can save people a bunch of money, and maybe some people in your parish, they have
insurance policies that can cover big expenses for funerals maybe, but there are also people
in your parish that do not have that.
And why would you be doing them a beautiful, beautiful ministry, a beautiful blessing
to take this up?
So I just want to throw that out there and recommend that to people.
I think it's a powerful thing to do.
So I mean...
What did people do before there were funeral homes?
You know it turned out that actually this was this was a community thing so yep
Yes
so
Yeah, and in terms of Christian practice
That sort of doesn't end with the funeral. Yeah
the
in that we have...
And traditionally those are done at the on the third day, the ninth day, the 40th day, and then yearly, right, like annually, on or around the date of the persons departure.
And in particular, those on the 3rd, 9th and 40th day,
are related to Christian traditions regarding the entrance of the person into
well life after death, not life after life after death.
Yes, that's later.
From our point of view, the connection of the soul to the body, of the person's life
to the body.
chiefly that for 40 days, well, first of all, traditionally Christians have believed that the ed experience, that belief is based on experience,
that the soul of the departed person remains connected to the world in a certain way.
near in a certain way during that 40-day period. And that the third and ninth days
relate to significant points on that journey that the soil is undertaking during that 40 days.
We believe there is purification happening during those 40 days.
No, we're not about to talk about toll houses. Some people are getting really excited there.
Yes, we will rev it up, rev it their edges.
But needless to say, a very literal understanding of the toll houses and or something like purgatory and or probably other things is trying to literalize and systematize things like way too much in terms of what Christianity is traditionally taught, but that is still a thing.
And of course, at those...
memorials, probably the most prominent slash memorable hymn is when we sing memory
eternal. And this is kind of an interesting inversion of the pagan Greek
belief, cultural belief, where it was about the memory of the person who
be kept alive amongst humans to sort of keep them alive in the afterlife.
Yes, we are talking about God remembering the person.
Right.
That's what memory eternal is about.
Christ remembering the person when he comes into his kingdom.
Yeah, divine memory, which is much more stable in lasting than human memory.
And then that is also celebrated with Kolyva, which is a kind of boiled wheat.
which is
Connected to our belief in the resurrection
And that's an important thing and father Andrew didn't you know specifically jump up and down on this but he mentioned it
Throughout the discussion he just did of clergy funerals is that all of our funeral and memorial services are all deeply connected to
The resurrection. Oh, yeah big time like there's right the scripture readings
The hymns.
which is why it's not like a very blunt even about death the reality of death, but also then always
pointing to the resurrection. Yeah, which is why, frankly, this whole celebration of life
nonsense kind of suggests you don't really believe in the resurrection. You know,
it kind of does that's it. Right, so like let's not dwell on this. Let's, you know, like say goodbye
So it's nice to know in here
Yeah, well, and the truth is, is our whole kind of
the funeral industry that we have is all designed to try to,
I shouldn't say all designed.
There's a lot about it, about the way we do with death
and dying and stuff.
That's about like, well, let's just keep it nice,
and clean and neat, and out of sight, out of mind.
Yeah, and honestly, I think that's a lot of what
why people do cremation is...
seems neat.
Yeah, well, yeah.
But it's yeah, I mean, our American version is very
distorted, right?
People rarely even see your contact the person's body.
Yeah, right?
Sort of whisked away after they they pass away.
Yep.
You know, the futile's done.
Let's put the ground a lot of times close casket the whole time.
That's it.
You know, and that actually doesn't help people grieve.
No, no, it doesn't.
That enhances people's sense that that person is just gone.
No, and some people like, well, you know, they'll even have a sense.
And I can always tell when people think this way because they're like,
they don't want to bring kids to funerals.
You know, oh, well, they're just kids.
I'm like, yeah, they're kids.
This is we're all gonna be there someday, you know?
That's gonna be everything one of us.
I brought my kids with a bunch of funerals,
even people that didn't know.
I should say, I brought them.
My wife is the one who always made a point of bringing them.
You know, while I was up doing the pre-sting,
she made sure she got the kids to the funerals.
And you know, they're not these morbid, traumatized people.
They understand what death is.
Well, this is, we have such a goofy view, right?
right i mean
let's be honest for most of human history
Okay. Kids saw the bodies while they were still kids of not only the grandparents, if
they got to know them at all, but their parents. We look at life expectancy. They were involved
in it. They saw dead bodies. Yeah. They saw dead bodies in their villages. They saw
dead bodies in human history now. Right. Most of human history. Kids saw it all the time.
every generation was not traumatized.
until the current one. Okay. As it aside, no one needed the birds at bees talk,
because they lived on farms that had animals. Right? That didn't scar any kids
psyched. Right? They figured out how things work. Right? Like there is this weird...
Right, I mean, certainly you want to protect...
that children from being victimized, right, from having crimes committed against them, right?
Definitely for sure, obviously, right?
But I think sometimes there's this idea that they need to be protected from reality.
Like this sort of fantasy land needs to be created for them to live in for some period
of time and then have that all crushed, you know.
The day that I told Santa Claus does not exist.
Hey, dude.
it doesn't exist and that's so basically they reach a certain age and realize that their parents have
been lying to them about all kinds of things. And what do you think that does with handing on your
religious beliefs to your children? Yeah. Right. How many kids decide that all that religion stuff was
the same was in the same bucket? Is all the other things you told them about the world that weren't true?
Anyway, I'm a big reality fan, not reality television because it's not real.
But actual reality.
Yeah, so now since we're coming to the end of the episode,
Well, they're in you probably has
Paper clips or toothpicks or something holding his eyelids open right now
But the creative episode.
So now why? Why all this?
Well, for one thing,
think for a minute about the continuities.
That you see running through everything we just talked about.
There's certainly discontinuities, right?
And you certainly see in Christian burial practices
Memorial Practice.
is a fulfillment, a correction, a fullness of the reality of life and death that is not
as clear, is not as unambiguous in the other things.
In fact, there's some errors, some idolatry in things that have snuck into a lot of those
earlier things.
But still look at the continuity.
Look at throughout human history and way back into prehistory as far back as we could go in prehistory
Right
Is that
Family in Kenya
Potentially possibly
Supposedly 84,000 years ago
is what they're experiencing when they buried their child that different from...
a couple that has to bury a child today.
Yeah.
And even the way that's reflected in the burial.
There is something about the truth,
which we see in its fullness revealed in Christianity,
there is something about that that,
that low and behold is essential to human nature because we were...
made in the image of Christ. This kind of basic understanding.
This basic understanding.
Relatedly as a corollary, I think if you understand that continuity,
you understand what we've been talking about tonight, and you can see that,
you will understand much better why the Orthodox Church forbids cremation.
Yeah, that practices of creation are a rejection of that part of our humanity, that sort
of human throughline.
The course has its basis in Christ, right, and in the resurrection.
Now those early homo sapiens, those early Neanderthals.
didn't know who Jesus of Nazareth was. They didn't know what a Nazareth was. They didn't know what a Messiah was.
per se.
You know, if anybody was going to rise from the dead, right?
Nonetheless,
aren't those practices
that they practiced with their departed loved ones?
Grounded in. A shadowy vague
maybe even in places erroneous understanding of Christ's resurrection.
Yeah, you know why go to all that effort, right? And obviously some in some of these cases,
some of these burial practices require way more effort than others. Like building a
the Kyrgyn is a lot of effort.
But it's still a lot of effort to like
dig out a hole in limestone cave.
You know, but either way it's it's not just oh this person's dead, you know get rid of that body
There's a bunch of effort that's put into this. It's clearly there's clearly ritual practices. There's focus on that person and
Yeah, it's it's one of the most deeply human things to do
To bury someone
You know and I mean
Like cremation, I think a lot of people do not realize what cremation actually entails.
You know, it's, you know, the human body is put basically inside a big oven and the bones
get ground up, smashed into pieces.
It's very violent to the human body.
If there's any metal, you know, like there's any prosthetic bits or whatever, they get tossed
like a big
and then like recycle or something like that.
It's very, yeah, it's,
you know, some people have asked sometimes,
like, well, you know,
what about saints who are burned alive
or whatever is part of their martyrdom?
Like, yeah, obviously the people who did that
should not have done that.
You know, and we don't, we still venerate those.
Right, people alive is bad, everyone.
Yeah, right, right.
We still venerate those relics.
But then to think that that's the right thing
to do.
you know, and again, I know that a lot of people do it because they've been told it's
the cheapest option. Number one, that is not always true. And number two, I'm just going
to repeat what I said earlier, I think parishes need to start these burial ministries. We've
accepted that this is something we hire out for way too long.
You know, if your parish does not have a burial ministry, think about starting one.
You know, it can be done.
And you'd be surprised at how many people would join you when you start to have conversations
about it, how important it will be to other people.
Like, okay, this is the thing that we do when one of our people dies.
You know, I mean, there's a whole book in the Bible that's based around the importance of
burying people.
And that's Tobit.
Right.
for this is that yes, that was considered, right, this is again part of second-templar
Jewish version that we've received in the church.
Caring for the dead is considered one of the greatest acts of love that you can do for
a person.
Yes, especially because they can't do anything for you back.
Yes, yes.
This is what Dwight Hoban is such a righteous man as that he goes and finds these people
who have died or been killed, right?
Whose bodies have just been left, have just been abandoned.
He goes...
he gives them a proper burial. And the process as a Jewish man makes himself unclean.
But he's up and goes through the process, right? He's willing to give that up in order to help
this person who could do nothing in return. Yeah. And this is the context for understanding,
like, you know, there's a point where when Christ calls someone to follow him and he says, I have
I have to go bury my father.
He says, let the dead bury their dead.
By no means is Jesus saying,
don't bury the dead.
It's, you're making excuse not to do
what you've been called to do, buddy.
That's what that's about.
He's not upending the whole tradition,
the whole commandments from God.
The proof of that is the end of every gospel.
Because who ends up getting
praised at the end of every gospel. Yeah. Yeah.
Joseph of Arimathea and the Murbearing women. Yeah. Yeah.
Exactly. Who did what? Who buried Christ? Yeah.
And we're told repeatedly, we're told repeatedly
by those gospels that they didn't know he was going to rise
from the debt. That's right. So that it was just an act of
love and even an active risk on their part.
Yes, they risk their lives to bury this person.
And how many people, including a bunch of the disciples,
said, well, we thought he was going to be the Messiah, but I guess not.
Yeah.
And went back to fishing.
It's these more marginal people.
Right, but they didn't. They risk their lives to go and bury Christ.
That's why they're considered such great saints.
Yeah.
So this is a whole thing.
And so these burial societies aren't just,
oh, this is a nice thing for your church to do,
you know, to help people because of our current economic realities
with the price of funerals in the United States or whatever.
This is one of the most powerful ministries,
In terms of the path of salvation, the path that leads to safe.
hood. This is one of the most powerful ministries a layperson can get involved in. Yeah. Yeah, I
so I think to summarize like to me the takeaway from a lot of this, I already mentioned, yeah,
I just want to double and triple down on that. But what is it so it does something for the
the people.
doing it right it's not only for the person who's dead it's not even only for
their family who I mean think about what that would be like it comes time to
bury your father your mother your husband your wife your child and instead of
and God bless them I honor what they do but instead of bringing in a
professional.
It's your community that you pray with that comes together and picks them up and lays
them out and close them and prays over them and digs their grave and lowers them into
it.
Think about that.
Think about how powerful that would be for you.
Now think about if you're one of the people doing that.
You are having direct contact with...
the body of a Christian, of a dead Christian, the part of Christian.
And the reality of what the resurrection means becomes very tangible for you, very tangible.
And not only going to a funeral, but you are connected with it.
You know, it's funny.
a lot of times people say, well when I come to church, you know.
What are we just supposed to stand there, whatever?
Like look, here's an opportunity.
If you want to, you know, get your hands involved
in something, here's an opportunity to do that.
Like really, for real.
And the last thing I'll say about how powerful this is
is as our 21st century continues on
first century continues on and life becomes more and more dematerialized.
ex-carinated, virtualized, and people think that words on a screen are more real than anything else.
This provides a haven for the souls that have been ground down by that reality.
It provides a haven. It says, here is a place where we take you and all of your three-denous, very seriously.
And this is what we do.
So it's good for the departed, it's good for their family, it's good for those engaged
in the ministry, and it is an evangelistic act.
It's an evangelistic act.
If our funerals are so evangelistic all on their own, think of how powerful it will be,
someone sees, oh, this is the way that we're cared for in this community.
I want.
That I want that
Yeah, this is not a marginal thing this is this is this is very very powerful
And so many ways so many ways so I'm grateful we did this episode
So yeah just briefly second I can hear father Andrew nodding off
I sort of can't get past our, well, our, frankly, our ancestor because we're, if it's
anything even remotely similar to 84,000 years ago, even if it's a tenth of that, even
if it's less than a tenth of that, we're all biologically related to these folks.
couple who had to bury there.
toddler and put them in a grave with a pillow under their head and a blanket
wrapped around them. And when they did that, they treated the body of their child
that way, they testified to the fact that love is more powerful than death. And I
I don't know how they could have intellectually known how that was true,
because it was only really revealed how that was true millennial later,
when Christ's love for us brought him to the most horrible death humans could
and then out the other side in the resurrection.
but that truth was in a shadowy way real to them nonetheless.
And I think we as Christians need to take that truth seriously.
And that's reflected in what Father Andrew has been talking about with the burial ministry,
but that's also reflected in how we think about the people we've known
the people we've loved.
who have departed this life before us.
Everything in our culture is aimed at when we need to quote unquote help you to quote
unquote move on to leave them behind.
But if it's true that our love for them is more powerful than death, then...
Now, these are no reason to leave them behind.
Why would you?
One of the gifts of being appraced
is that I have a sort of very real way to do this
and that as I'm preparing for liturgy each time on the patent
I can remember those people
before God by name.
A subset of those people I get to do to celebrate memorial services so far.
But there are some of those people who I sort of carry with me all the time. I'm not talking about their
memory. I'm out of them. In Christ, they're still alive. Yes, I know. There's a bunch of these people
who haven't been glorified as saints.
And sometimes I'm talking about, I'm not talking about I'm writing Traparia for them and
we're going to celebrate the liturgy for my dad.
Right?
Sometimes I talk about.
But that also doesn't mean he has somehow ceased to exist or somehow gone from me in my
life or any of the other people who are in that category.
And as I'm getting older, there's more and more people falling into that.
category and that's just going to continue until I join them. A lot of that is
realized in prayer.
praying for the departed, praying with the departed.
Continuing that bond.
But so I hope...
what people will walk away from this episode with is that fundamental truth that we see so clearly in Christ that love is more powerful than death, and then actually put that into action in your life, in your awareness of the fact that the departed in Christ are not separated from us.
They are not gone.
We are not moving on from them.
That they're continuing...
doing company us through life in a different way. And that's a different way that in the Christian
hope is going to lead to reunion. That's what I have to say about that. Amen. Amen. Well, that's our
show for tonight, everyone. Thank you very much for listening. If you didn't happen to get through to
us live to call on the phone, we'd still like to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of Spirit
It's ready.
You can also send us a message on our Facebook page.
You can leave a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of
Spirits and if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to
find a parish to live this 3D life, go to Orthodoxintro.org
Enjoy us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m.
Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific, weird times.
So, shame is the prison as cruel as a grave.
Shame is a robber.
He's come to take.
my name. If you're on Facebook you can follow our page, you can also join our discussion group,
leave ratings and reviews and all the places and share this show with a friend.
And probably be sure to go to www.AxraPayth.com.stokes.com to support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air. Well, fear is a liar with a smooth and velvet tongue,
fear is a tyrant, it's always telling me to run. Thank you, good night and God bless you all.
He's been...
listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands, saying with
a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength.
An honor and glory in blessing.
Revelation chapter...